<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to the Greeks, especially to those in and about Corinth and Athens with certain queries propounded to the priests and doctors, and all the rest of the members and officers belonging unto the two churches of Greeks and Romans, which is of concernment for the view of them all throughout the world / written in Egripo in the island of Negroponte by a servant of the Lord, J.P.</title>
            <author>J. P. (John Perrot), d. 1671?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32179</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12353604</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12353604</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1025:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to the Greeks, especially to those in and about Corinth and Athens with certain queries propounded to the priests and doctors, and all the rest of the members and officers belonging unto the two churches of Greeks and Romans, which is of concernment for the view of them all throughout the world / written in Egripo in the island of Negroponte by a servant of the Lord, J.P.</title>
                  <author>J. P. (John Perrot), d. 1671?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Perrot by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE TO THE GREEKS.</p>
            <p>ESPECIALLY To thoſe in and about <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Athens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Certain <hi>Queries</hi> propounded to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi> and all the reſt of the Members and Officers belonging unto the two Churches of <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> which is of concernment for the view of them all throughout the WORLD.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Egripo</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Negroponte,</hi> By a Servant of the Lord: <hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth,</hi> within <hi>Alderſgate.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60053:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Word of the Lord is the Proclamation of War, onely with the wicked, and the meſſengers thereof holds not the perſons of men in contempt, or ſcorne; it caſteth out the root of envy, which Satan planted in the heart, and fixeth the love of God for the ſouls inheritance, which floweth in pitty, and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in mercy to others! He that readeth and receiveth, in him alſo hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and he ſhall bear Teſtimony to the Truth and witneſſe for God, that the zeal of the Lords Houſe is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Envy, Emulation, Wrath, or vain Contention. Wherefore I ſay, God who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mercy, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bountifully of the riches of his Grace unto me, hath freed me from the nature of evill towards my neighbour, and hath given me of his Love therewith to ſeek the loſt, from which iſſues the plainneſſe of my Declarations and Speeches, which without guile, fraud, or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries; Love in ſimplicity holds forth the Truth in nakedneſſe, and this will ſtand a Yoak to the ſtubborn, and a Dart in the ſide of the rebellions; The enmity is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; He that hath an ear to heare, let him heare. This is verily a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the ſame nature of what follows in the ſuccedent <hi>Pages.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Given forth by a Friend in the Truth, A lover of ſouls, <hi>J. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60053:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Day will declare the Dreadfull and Mighty Work.</head>
            <p>IN the Councel of the wonderfull Counceller, and All mighty Father, and Fountaine of Wiſdom, (who confoundeth the Councils of the wiſe, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Fathers of this world, in whoſe ſight the prudent and learned amongſt men, are but as fools plotting in their works, the contrivance and invention of the perpetual evil of their ſouls.) This is given forth to the only true intent, that the ſimple hearted may be rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the way to ſalvation, life and peace everlaſting: For of a truth the Lord God of Heaven and earth is ariſen, who for many hundreds of years hath been as a ſtranger up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth: And now in this his mighty day which is broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and breaking forth by the work of his own hand, he will fruſtrate <hi>the tokens of lyars, and make the Diviners mad,</hi> and turn wiſe men backward, and make their knowledge fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who will open a door to the ſimple, and lead the Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men, and fools, in the unerring path of Righteouſneſſe, and the deceit in the earth, ſhall no longer ſtand (without a heavy work) as it did in the dayes of the ancient Fathers, Doctors, and Lawyers of the world, who took from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the key of knowledge, who entred not in themſelves, but ſtood in the gap, and ſet Bryars and Thorns in the way, and hindred ſuch as was entring. The flame of the fire of the Lord will finiſh the courſe of the former times; for, ſhall it not burn in a dry Countrey? And if the Nations poſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Euphrates</hi> for water to quench the fire, ſhall not that River be alſo dryed up before they come there? And if from thence they flye unto <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſhall not the utter Conſumption be, ere they can have help from thence? <hi>Behold the Lord will make a quick work in the earth.</hi> Let the Nations therefore repent; and now not in any upbraiding, or raſh judging man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but in the Councel of God, as a ſervant by Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60053:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in the work of the Lord, in love unſpeakable to all ſouls, I ſhew unto the people their ſtates, and unto the ſons of men how they ſtand in the ſight of God, my teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaching that of God in mens conſciences, to the meaſure of the Light in all, deſiring only to be made manifeſt, which, when the ſinner is convinced of his ſins, and the wicked man converted in his mind, and turned from the evill of his wayes, then ſhall they confeſſe of a truth, the bleſſed day of the Lord; and ſay, Surely it was well for us, that the Prophet ſpared not, to ſhew unto <hi>Judah</hi> her ſins, and unto <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> her tranſgreſſions; Yea well ſprang forth that day, and that hour, was the certain timely ſeaſon of the appearance of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and manifeſtation of loving kindneſſe, wherein <hi>Nathan</hi> was ſent to ſhew unto <hi>David</hi> the treachery and rebellion of his heart. And now what am I that God ſhould remember me, alſo with the mercies of <hi>David</hi> to ſhew me my tranſgreſſion, that by his word I may be converted and healed?</p>
            <p>Verily of none other do I make mention, but only of the name of the <hi>Holy One,</hi> and that which proceedeth from his preſence, declaring this Dread, ſhewing unto all people the Door of mercy, the Fountain of life, the Gate of knowledge, &amp; everlaſting treaſure of undefiled pure wiſdome. For as much as the Lord holdeth forth a day of viſitation unto all, that the whole world may be left without excuſe in the day of Gods dreadful judgements, when the compleat fulfilling and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the time cometh to paſſe, of the full gathering of the ſcattered Seed, in the Fields of the Earth, and full calling of his Remnant from the four windes of the Heavens, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Nations, Kindreds, Countryes, Tongues and Peoples; and the Lord haſteth the Reaping of the Harveſt. A warning to the World to repent, and this to the Debtors, and Captives of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is ſounded, and ſounding. The year of Jubilee beginneth in the morning ſeaſon, yet a little while, and your ſlumber will be over, and the clouds of the night will paſſe from the ſphear of your low degree, which ariſeth, and will quickly paſſe over the Sun of another exalted Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Oh how doth the day change the times, the Children
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60053:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are become Dogs, and the Dogs which were, are become the glory of the earth; and who hath an eye to ſee, or a heart to believe, that this is come, it cometh, and is at hand, that the Dogs ſhall eat the Childrens bread, and no more ſhall their name be a reproach among the Gentiles, but their day of Son-ſhip ſhall be the Dread of the Heathen.</p>
            <p>Who is he now that will ſet Briars in the way, or Thorns in the breach of the Gap which the Lord hath made, and who is he that contendeth againſt his maker, ſaying, why cometh this thing to paſſe, mine hand is turned againſt it? <hi>Ye deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and wonder, and periſh, behold I work a work in your dayes, which if a man ſhall tell it unto you, ye ſhall in no wiſe believe it.</hi> And you that reſiſt, are but for the conſumption of the fire of Gods jealouſie, in the day of his wrath.</p>
            <p>A warning, a warning to the whole world is come, it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, it hath ſounded, and is ſounding. The mighty day of God is at hand; therefore whileſt you have time, repent.</p>
            <p>And allthough the <hi>Gentiles</hi> reſiſt, and all the Heathen eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where gain-ſay, yet the Lord will be glorified over all the world, unto whom the Light is the ſure meſſage of the Moſt High, whether they will hear or forbear.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60053:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE TO THE GREEKS.</head>
            <p>I Have heard a rumor in mine ears of a hard cry among the people; Alas, alas! Our glory is defaced, and our ancient praiſe and renown is utterly defamed; Our wives are made the Vaſſals of other women, and we are become ſlaves to a ſtrange Nation; We are no more under the Government of the Scepter, which ſwayed our Fathers, but the wills of another people works violence over us; Our houſes are but as habitations lent unto us, and our ſubſtance and portion, at pleaſure may be ſpoyled by the hand of the Devourer; Our children unto us are not as were the children of our fore-fathers in their Generations our wives and children, treaſure and ſubſtance, is but a burden unto us, when the eyes of our Lords looks over us. Alas, alas! our miſery is great, and none regardeth it, the ſound of our cry hath reached far, yet few have pondered it. And the Lord ſaid unto me, Cry alſo among the Profeſſors of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, even thus it is come to paſſe in many Regions of the earth, the bondage it great, and the captivity is doubled with violence, and with cruelty; The chains and yoaks are twice laid on, and the people are under the indignation of the Lord: The judgements of their adverſaries lyes heavy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heads, and their Loins are banded with the oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Rulers, as with Iron and with Braſſe, and they cannot break the Cords to caſt off their burdens; and this,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60053:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and much more, is the miſery of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> which their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers iniquities firſt brought upon their heads in their dayes, and the children of their Generations drinking of the Cup of their abominations, unto this preſent Seed of evill doers; Wherefore the hand of vengeance ſtill toucheth their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and in this manner God hath ſeen it equall, to lay the burden upon that man, which with his tranſgreſſions hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and preſſed down the righteous ſoul of the Lord, as a Cart is laden, and preſſed down with ſheaves.</p>
            <p>This is the end of their labours, they ploughed the fields of the pleaſure of their own hearts, they ſowed the ſeed of unrighteouſneſſe in the depth of the ground of iniquity, who notwithſtanding the Lord watered them with the water of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, yet returned they not in the day of affliction, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of corruption they have reaped this abundance of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>YE <hi>Greeks</hi> unto whom I write, for the ſeeds ſake, as a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band unto a wife, not covering the diſeaſed parts, or falſly ſolving up the foreſt, and moſt dangerous wounds, not ſeeking to ſeal up your ſtates in hidden ſentences from your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, or your conditions in parables, nor to ſhut the door of the Kingdom againſt the ſeed of the Kingdom. It hath pleaſed the Lord, (contrary to every part of the natural, and deſire of the carnall) to lead me through ſome of the Countryes, wherein as Sojourners you are Inhabitants, among whom I did earneſtly ſeek, but could not find, and then I returned to the Lord, and ſought with tears, yet truly could not find one in a City that was worthy; Ye ought to bear with me for the Truths ſake, nevertheleſs, whether you will hear or forbear; for the Lords ſake, and his ſeeds ſake, I am obliged by that which ſtretcheth forth love unto ſouls, in this manner to ſtretch forth mine hand, to draw back the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that you may look to the Light which breaks through the Lattice, and to remove the skirt which it folded over your nakedneſſe, that your eye may ſee your filthineſſe.</p>
            <p>O miſery, miſery, the ſeed is in bondage, that's your greateſt miſery within, the burdens of which is the ground of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60053:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
your miſery without; Conſider, conſider, and lay it to heart, uſe diligence in the ſearch of your hearts, for the Lord God cometh quickly, to try and to ſearch every heart, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and give unto all according to their deeds done in the body, whether they be good, or whether they be evil.</p>
            <p>Conſider your Life, which is the ground, and cauſe of the <hi>mourning of the Land.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 23.10.</note> I have paſſed through you, and have ſeen the life of your people; Behold abominable ſwearing, lying, cheating, coveting, drunkenneſs, whoredom, adultery, murder;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.23.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Changing the glory of the incorruptible God, into Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, made like unto corruptible man. Wherefore God alſo hath given you up to uncleanneſſe, through the luſts of your corrupt hearts. Who have changed the truth of God into a lye, and to worſhip and ſerve the Image of the creature, more than the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.</hi> Whoſe own Image only praiſeth him, who is bleſſed over all for ever, and evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is truth in the preſence of the Lord God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and unto the Light of Chriſt which ſhines in all your Conſciences, which ſhews you all your ſins, even unto that true Witneſſe in your own hearts I ſpeak. I have been an eye witneſſe of the bowing of the bodies of many of your people, unto the works of your Fathers idolatrous hands, unto which your corrupt hearts and deceitfull affections are joyned, whileſt not one of you in a Nation, which mine eye ever beheld, came to bow his heart in Righteouſneſſe, and his life in Spirit and Truth before the Lord God who is a Spirit,<note place="margin">John 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſe day cometh, and now is, that the true Worſhippers do worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for as much as Ye, with other Idolaters, do make theſe few following dark words, the ſeeming ground of your ſtanding places, ſaying, <hi>Viz. That you are the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, and that you believe in Chriſt, and do believe the Words and Doctrine of Chriſt, the Scriptures of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and writings of the Apoſtles, and that you hold the Precepts, and do follow the inſtructions of the ancient Fathers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60053:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> You whoſe Fathers made many Temples, and painted Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures therein, that they might worſhip and bow down unto the works of their own hands. Ye ſee the day in the midſt of your calamities, and time of ſorrows, how that many of the houſes which they built are left unto you deſolate. And if now you the ſeed of the corruption of their generation, were but come to the loſſe of your Fathers naturall Image in your carnal hearts and affections; You would alſo as clearly diſcern your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miſery, which through the groſſe vail of darkneſſe over your hearts, is hid from your eyes. Oh the captivity, the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, you are held in the poſſeſſion of bondage and captivity, under the profeſſion of the name of Chriſt and Chriſtians, in the luſts of unrighteouſneſſe, and the pleaſures of ſin and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and this hath brought blindneſs, and ſpread ignorance as a thick cloud which covers the underſtanding part, wherefore you are ſtrangers unto, and as a people not having knowledge of the ſeed of God, which notwithſtanding the hardſhips of your outward ſufferings, and the ſcourge of your bodyes, yet the ſeed of the Kingdome lyes laden with your lightneſſe, and is heavily preſſed down with the exceſſive weight of your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſſe oaths, and other abominable ſins and tranſgreſſions; Ye are blinded, ye are blinded, through the multitude of your corruptions; your whole body is become a lump of miſery; You daily add murder unto miſchief, without reſpect, or any regard to the life of the innocent, and after your adulteries, you retain not the thought of the ſuccour of the life of the Virgin Daughter, which ye have abuſed through the luſts of uncleanneſſe, and ſo you add ſin unto ſin, binding your ſelves under the perpetual oath and curſe of cruelty, in the bondage of your own miſery, and capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. Wo is me for you, the love of my bowels to the ſeed is made a brook of bitterneſs in my belly; For your ſakes I am as one that hath eaten affliction, and ſwallowed up ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, as in the day of trouble. Oh how hath the night been te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to my watchful eyes, which the ſtrength of your miſeries kept open, when ſlumber had no power to ſhut them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now I call, and with a loud voice lifted over your Land, I cry, <hi>Come forth ye careleſſe minds, ſtretch forth your feet, ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60053:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hearts, out of the Bed of the miſerable ſlumber of your ſtarved ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Awake, awake to the mourning, and ariſe and come forth to the lamentation, for your loſſe. O weep, weep for the woe is your own, for your own wickedneſſe. Conſider and lay it to heart, ſhould not the hour of diſtreſſe bring ſorrows and mourning upon your hearts? Oh wherefore then hath the Lord looked, and behold your Land hath been filled with lightneſſe, and ye have not forgotten the vain words of the former Generation, but with a fooliſh confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence have believed and truſted in their lyes, as if the credit of the deceitfull words of their wicked inventions, ſhould ſtand the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your miſerable ſinfull ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing therefore unto this day ye have been groſſely delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deceived, under the profeſſion of the name of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholique Church,</hi> I ſhall anſwer the vanity of your Faith, with a few words of Truth. God who in the dayes of old choſe unto himſelf a peculiar people of the ſeed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> alſo in the fulneſſe of the diſpenſation of time, ſent his onely begotten Son a Light into the world, that the world through him (who is the Light) might believe, and have everlaſting life, by whom the Apoſtles and Saints in them dayes were gathered unto God, and were made Members of the <note place="margin">Heb. 12.23. Acts 20.28. Matth. 16.18.</note>
               <hi>Church of the firſt born which are written in Heaven, who is the Reſurrection of the dead,</hi> and of this Church of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>of which Chriſt is now the Head,</hi> as he was in the dayes of the Apoſtles, who wrote of this Church, who therefore was, and is the Head; <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.13. Coloſſ. 1.18.</note>
               <hi>That he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, not having spot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh, and that in all things he might have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence.</hi> And of this, and none other Church, did the Lord ſpeak, and the Apoſtles write; but as for the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, neither have I by any teſtimony heard, or by any writing of the true Prophets, the Declaration of Chriſt, or in the writings of the Apoſtles, read of any ſuch Church ſhould be, as of the Truth, or ſtand as in the Truth, or that unto the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, the Truth ſhould be only committed; Allthough this I ſay, that the Scriptures do make mention, that once there was an aſſembly of Saints which lived in <hi>Rome,</hi> as there did alſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60053:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in other places and parts of the earth, among whom the truth was in power received, in the day of the proſperity thereof, untill the time of the apoſtacy came in, and the working of the miſtery of iniquity waxed great and ſpread over the face of the earth, even among all people who received the ſound of the Declaration of the birth of a Son in the City of <hi>David,</hi> Jeſus the Chriſt, whom the Prophets propheſied of, ſhould come; and of this apoſtacy and falling away, Chriſt himſelf, (who is the ſum and ſubſtance of the Law and the Prophets) ſpake of, ſaying; <note place="margin">Math. 24.24.</note>
               <hi>There ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders, in ſo much that if it were poſſible, they ſhould deceive the very Elect.</hi> And this iniquity began to work in the dayes of the Apoſtles, of which <hi>John</hi> in this manner did write, <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.18, 19.</note> by which he knew that it was the laſt time as they had heard that Antichriſt ſhould come, and ſaith he,<note place="margin">1 John 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>even now there are many Antichrists;</hi> Wherefore he alſo exhorted the Brethren, that they ſhould not believe every Spirit, but to try the Spirits, whether they are of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets were then gone into the world. And <hi>Paul,</hi> he teſtifieth his knowledge, ſaying,<note place="margin">Acts 20.29.30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>After my departing ſhall grievous Wolves enter in among you, not ſparing the flock, and alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things to draw many Diſciples after them; therefore watch and remember, that by the ſpace of three years I ceaſed not to warn every one night and day with teares.</hi> And this in meaſure came to paſſe whileſt <hi>John</hi> was; <hi>Paul</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">John 1.9, 10. 1 Theſſ. 2.7.8, 9</note> he bore further witneſſe that this thing muſt be, even the falling away, elſe this day, which is now come, and coming could not come: and he ſaid then in his day alſo, <hi>That the Myſtery of iniquity doth already work, only he who letteth, will let, untill he be taken out of the way, and then ſhall that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſſe of his coming, even him whoſe coming</hi> (mark his coming) <hi>is after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders, and with all deceivableneſſe of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, in them that periſh, and for this cauſe ſeeing they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the love of the Truth, God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they ſhould believe a lye, that they all might be damned, who believed not the Truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe;</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60053:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
In which ſtate and condition of vanity and unrighteouſneſſe, I find the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholique Churches, as a people miſerably ſpoyled,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.8.</note> through the deceit of vain Philoſophy, <hi>Walking after the Traditions of men, after the Rudiments of the world, in the unrighteouſneſſe and uncleanneſſe thereof, in fornication and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, in drunkenneſſe, pride, malice and murder, lying and ſwearing, vain jeſting, and fooliſh talking,</hi> As a people through the abominable luſts of uncleanneſs in your lives, void of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or at leaſt wiſe not conſidering, and laying it to heart, how <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.5.</note>
               <hi>That no unclean perſon, nor Idolater hath any inheritance in the Kingdome of Chriſt, and of God;</hi> being as it were ſtupified and benummed in your ſenſes, ſo far degenerated from the power of Truth, and myſtery of Godlineſs, that ye have loſt the generall forme, and do retain but the leaſt part thereof; wherefore among you, and upon you, the words and propheſie of the Apoſtle is fulfilled, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13.</note>
               <hi>Evill men and Seducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived.</hi> And yet a little while, and it ſhall alſo be ſhewn unto you that deſire to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, wherein you are fallen below the form of the profeſſion of Godlineſs, as in divers particulars I ſhall query for the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your underſtandings, that by your diligent ſearch in the Scripture with the Light you may ſee, which will effectually make for the manifeſtation of the ground of your cuſtomes and practices, in your idolatrous and ſuperſtitious worſhips. And this unto you all is held forth, for the tryal of your wayes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lords mighty day is at hand, which will rip open and make manifeſt all hearts, and declare and preach that which hath been hid in ſecret upon the houſe tops. Many of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were the worſhippers of the works of the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> untill the ſound of the fame of Chriſt came among them, whoſe Miracles and Reſurrection confounded the depth of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their wiſdom, by which the wiſe men came to confeſſe a greater than themſelves, which ſuddenly rang through the Nation, and ſo from Nation to Nation, from the report and credit of the confeſſion of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and learned <hi>Doctors,</hi> the ignorant alſo in all your Nations joyned with the humane learned, and ſo with one conſent they cryed up the name (to wit) of Chriſt, whereof they had received the report, who ſometime before that had ſlaughtered the Apoſtles, who fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60053:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their teſtimonies in the Life and Spirit of Jeſus, holding forth his name in power, whoſe name in words, as the Apoſtacy came and grew as the deceivers, and falſe Prophets, and falſe Brethren, and falſe Apoſtles went forth, your Fathers the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> and wiſe men came to confeſſe; mark the time of the coming in of this, which at this time ye ſtand in, which had not an entrance, by the Doctrine or Example of <hi>Peter,</hi> or life and preaching of <hi>Paul,</hi> but by ſuch as was ſpoken of, ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the little flock of Chriſt, and make havock of the Heritage of God, concerning whom, I have ſhewn you <hi>Johns</hi> witneſs, and <hi>Pauls</hi> teſtimony, and yet furthermore do write <hi>Judes</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> propheſies; <note place="margin">Jude 4.</note>
               <hi>For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the grace of our God into laſciviouſneſſe, filthy dreamers, that defile the fleſh, murmerers, complainers, walking after their own luſts, and their mouth ſpeaking great and ſwelling words, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage;</hi> Such as the Apoſtles of our Lord ſpake of ſhould come; Mockers, who ſhould walk after their own ungodly luſts, who are ſenſual, having not the Spirit of Truth.</p>
            <p>To the Church ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>There ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, and many ſhall follow their pernicious ways, of whom the way of Truth ſhall be evill ſpoken of, having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot ceaſe from ſin, beguiling unſtable ſouls, and hearts they have exerciſed with covetous practices, curſed children which have forſaken the right way, who are the Angels which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habitations, God hath reſerved in the everlaſting chains under darkneſs, unto the judgement of the great day.</hi> Seeing therefore that the Scriptures are true, as is manifeſt by the coming of theſe things to paſſe, according to the words of the Apoſtles propheſies, and finding you in the curſed ground, and nature of uncleanneſs, bringing forth fruits of iniquity.</p>
            <p>Hereby I know, <hi>even by your fruits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 12.33.</note> into what ſtock you are grafted, mine inſtrument hath reached your root. And again, I ſay all men upon the face of the earth, who have the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, may truly underſtand that ye are in the Apoſtacy, working the unrighteous works of your Fathers, who were the firſt Apoſtates from the true Faith, in whom iniquity wrought
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60053:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in a myſtery, who when Satan had his end in deſtroying to the uttermoſt, in the ſlaughter of all the holy Apoſtles, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the <hi>Jews,</hi> after they had ſlaughtered the true Prophets, garniſhed their Tombs, in honour of their perſons, even ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo did the Deceiver ſet your Fathers a work to build Idols Temples, and to draw out the Saints Pictures, and to do hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the Pictures of Chriſt, <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Apoſtles, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their Perſons, and thoſe things which your Fathers built, ye garniſhed, wherein ye witneſſe that ye are their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and are filling up the meaſure of their iniquity; and thus the Devil gained his dominion in you, and among you, by transforming himſelf (in a nearer ſhape) like an Angel of Light, in divers other things and Ceremonies, and wrought in, and among your Fathers, as he did in the dayes of old among the ſons of men, who ſought out many Inventions, inſomuch that the righteous ſoul of God was grieved with them, ſo that God repented that he had made man; for ſtraightway after the ſpirit of Antichriſt had ſo greatly wrought through the earth, as that Nations came under, and in ſubjection to the wills of the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> even to the confeſſing of the name of Chriſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; Your Fathers they entered into divers conſultations, and what they ſought out by their Inventions, were ſet up as Laws and Ordinances, and Statutes in the forms of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and thus came in as I have ſaid, the buildings of <hi>Idols Temples,</hi> the carving of Images, the painting of pictures, the making of Beads and Croſſes of Wood, Bone, Stone, Gold, Silver, and other dead created things, and the Invention of Candles, and Lamps, and Altars, for your ſacrifices, and all manner of Surpleſſes, and deceitful coverings, and hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winking garments, the obſervations of times and ſeaſons, and weeks, and dayes, and divers other hereſies, and damnable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Devils, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1, 2.3.</note>
               <hi>Forbidding to marry, and to abſtain from meats, which God had created to be received with thanks-giving.</hi> All theſe and many more of your cuſtomes, and Idolatrous worſhips, are neither according to the command of God, or of Chriſt, or the preſident or example of the Holy Apoſtles, through the Witneſſe of the Scripture; In few words, the root of theſe things was the invention and working of iniquity, in the hearts of your Fathers, through the deceitful motions of Satan;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60053:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſo whereas you ſay, That you have the doctrine of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers. I anſwer, It is true, you ſtand in the error of their wayes, I ſee and ſavour you in the foot-ſteps of their ungodly luſts, as the Scriptures declares, and not only thoſe in the days of old, but alſo unto this time you have many Fathers upon earth, whereby your own confeſſion bears witneſſe againſt you that you have not learned of Chriſt, <hi>who is the way to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> which all that beleeve in him, have but one <hi>Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore in your prayers to <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſupplication to the Saints, to mediate and make interceſſion for you; O miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable blindneſs and lamentable darkneſſe, how ſtrongly hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan chained your hearts, that you lye under ſo great a cloud of ignorance? Oh what is your loſſe, through the vented concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the inventions of your Fathers, how in vain have they profeſſed the Scriptures, and in their words and ſmooth lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage owned Chriſt, and the doctrine of the Apoſtles, and how deſperately wicked, and unſpeakably deceitful, did the Devil work in his day? to bind you under the belief and credit of their unrighteouſneſs and falſhood, to hide knowledge from your eyes, by training you up only under the vail of their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, not giving you liberty to read the Scriptures, under the pretence that hereſies thereby might not creep into their Church, as if the knowledge of the Scriptures were the ground or cauſe of hereſies; but judge ye whether their doctrine is according to the Apoſtles inſtruction. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.5.</note>
               <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator, between God and men. Paul</hi> doth not ſay, that it was the woman <hi>Mary,</hi> which was eſpouſed to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or that it was an Apoſtle, which before him was offered up in the witneſſe of the holy Faith; neither doth he ſay, that he ſhould be the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceder, when after he ſhould have finiſhed his teſtimony, and be offered up alſo, but he truly teſtifieth of one Interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Mediator, the man Chriſt Jeſus. And likewiſe alſo the Spirit helpeth our infirmities, for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>but the Spirit it ſelfe maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us, with groanings which cannot be uttered. And he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, becauſe he maketh interceſſion for the Saints, according to the will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60053:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Greater Teſtimony cannot be declared unto you, then the putting you in remembrance of your fruits, which gives the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſavour and ſight of your eſtate; notwithſtanding, I know <hi>Romes</hi> learning will not fall ſo quickly, but her Fathers by <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry,</hi> will hold out, and ſtrive to ſtretch forth a leafe to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your miſery in iniquity; have not I already heard the Diſputer put forth his treacherous, deceitful, critical enquiry, if peradventure his arm might help to make a Fence about the Wall, which the hand of the Lord is digging down, hath it not been already ſaid by ſome of your Fathers, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>If the Apoſtaſie in that time came in, and ſince the time of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aughter of the Apoſtles, hath ſtood unto this day, where then in all the time ſince them dayes was the Church, which is the Body of which Chriſt is the Head? If ſince there hath not been a Church, how then is Chriſt the Head of the Church? but if ſince there hath been a Church, we then affirm that we are that Church (who have kept this our Faith of the Church) of which Chriſt is the Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, The woman hath been preſerved in the wilderneſs (mark) in her place in the wilderneſs, which God prepared for her,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.14, 15.</note> and there ſhe hath been nouriſhed for <hi>A time, and times, and halfe a time, from the face of the Serpent, and from the floods which the Dragon caſt out of his mouth after her;</hi> Your For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes and fenced Cityes, and ſtrong inhabited places, the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of your Idolatrous Temples, is not that wilderneſſe wherein God prepared the womans place of preſervation; In your City <hi>Rome,</hi> are the ſtreets which ſpiritually are called <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> where our Lord was, and is daily crucified. Idleneſs and fulneſs of bread, hath encreaſed your ſin in luſt and wantonneſs; Your Land is <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where the Onions, and the Garlick, and the Leeks, and the Milleons grow, and the fleſh-pots are, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which your hearts are bound with unreaſonable cords of Appetite; It is a mighty hand that muſt draw you, ere you be delivered out of the Land of bondage, of captivity, and ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to come to the knowledge, and to be joyned in your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and life, to the ſore travels of the ſeed, and Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord in the wilderneſſe; and by how much you are ſhort of this, you are ſhort of the knowledge of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of his faithfulneſſe <hi>in all Gods houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 12.7.</note> and by how much you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60053:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are ſhort of the life of <hi>Moſes,</hi> you are ſhort of the knowledge of <hi>Chriſt the Head, and of the Church</hi> the body; for <hi>Moſes</hi> he was a follower of Chriſt, who was raiſed up for the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſeed, with which your Fathers made war in their days, even with the Remnant, which was ſpared in the dayes of the coming in, and ſpreading of the Apoſtacy, which now the Lord hath returned, and is returning the captivity of, and hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and is delivering the woman out of the ſolitarineſſe of her flight, in a ſecret place in the wilderneſſe, whoſe tryals and travels, and refuge, and reſtauration, and redemption, ye are ignorant of; And your darkneſs through your corruption, and unrighteouſneſſe is the cauſe of your vain contentions againſt, and ſtumbling at the high-way of truth and peace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>And yet if you further enquire, in what eſtate and condition your Fathers and Predeceſſors ſtood in their day, which ye their ſucceſſors are entred into, and do ſtand in theſe dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, It was, and is the eſtate and condition of the world, in the nature of the world, in the abominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the world, <hi>who cannot ceaſe from ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14.</note> in the filthy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean luſts of the world, and in the deceit of Satan, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the world, under the pronunciation of the word of <hi>Johns</hi> propheſie. <note place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note>
               <hi>Woe to the Inhabiters of the earth, for the Devill is come down unto you, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> and this in brief is your eſtate, and time in which you ſtand.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I am aſſured in the truth, that as ye remain in the ground and nature of your curſed life, ye have not in the leaſt meaſure or appearance any good confidence to affirm that you are the true Church of Chriſt, but rather your arguments aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, and all manner of diſputations do ariſe from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of impudence, which hath a face to bear out your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and falacies. I know the figure of your Kingdome, (you who are called <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> alſo mark this your figure) the <hi>Chameli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> which lives by the Aire, which according to the Law is an unclean Beaſt, which can change himſelf into all colours, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect white onely excepted; Read your ſimilitude, and ſee how you who live in your luſts, can without a mock of the Truth, be titled with the name of the Church of Chriſt Jeſus, in which is neither ſpot, nor wrinkle, nor blemiſh, nor any ſuch thing as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60053:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
uncleanneſſe or unrighteouſneſſe;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>Although ſuch were ſome of them, but they came to be waſhed, and were cleanſed, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and juſtified, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of our God;</hi> Which Spirit of truth the light, is this day the Leader of the Saints and ſervants of God into all truth.</p>
            <p>Now therefore doe ye Read, What is the Chaffe to the Wheate? And what relation hath the Spirit of truth unto your life, which is ſquared and faſhioned in the frame of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror? Deceite hath been the Maſter-builder of the fabrick of your habitation, the ſpirit of Iniquitie working in a myſtery the foundation of your walls, and the ſtrength of lyes, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders, the pillars of your houſe, which by the gilded appearance of the beauty of the wiſdome of the ancient and learned in <hi>Philoſophy, Rhetorick,</hi> and <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> is covered with many painted tiles of vanitie, under the ſhaddow whereof you bow to the Images and pictures, which the unrighteous hearts of your fathers Invented, whoſe Gods are before your eyes, unto which the affections of your naturall ſences are joyned, whereby with the carnall and naturall, according to the motion of the Spirit of Error and Deceit in you, you are led to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the workes of their hands, as is manifeſt by your bowings and bendings to the Image and likeneſſe of the naturall, which the naturall invented, and the carnall made; And this alſo came in in the Apoſtaſie, when that was forſaken which the Eternall Spirit did command. And now through the cuſtome of your forefathers, and you in the dayly practice of their invented Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, being ſetled on the leeſe of their abominable Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, are come in your generation <note place="margin">Matth. 15.9.</note>
               <hi>to teach for doctrine the traditions of men.</hi> And therefore in vaine is your worſhip, as ſaith the Lord: But yet ye have alſo to ſpeake in the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of your fathers ſeniority and wiſdome, who gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement for ſuch reſemblances, by Images and pictures, not as if they were the gods of your worſhip, but the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances of the Lord Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whom by theſe reſemblances you teach the ignorant for to worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> The greateſt blindneſſe is in the hearts of your learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; I ſpeak out of the ſpheare of their <hi>Colledges;</hi> in mine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to their plea for their ſinfull Idolatries, and over all your Nations doe cry out and lift up my voyce as one in mourning,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60053:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
lamenting for the loſt ſeed among you, (which they that ſhould rather in righteouſneſſe handle the plow to break up the clods, to uncover the ſeed, have uſed the ſpade and ſhovel, and have heaped up dirt and ſtones thereon, to the miſerable burden thereof) Oh horrible Ignorance, a people bound with the chaines of darkneſſe; can any thing be the reſemblance of the Lord, or the likeneſſe of his Image, (who is the Infinite, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, a pure, holy, glorious, endleſſe, living Spirit) but that which he maketh in his likeneſs, and formeth in his own Image, by the power of his own Almighty hand; And doth he who is a pure Everlaſting Spirit of life, make or faſhion any whom he faſhioneth, but in the likeneſſe of that, which all the world by wiſdome, by <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> or by arguments can never attaine to reach unto the ſight or underſtanding thereof? Can any make the reſemblance of God, who is Immortall, which the mortall never ſaw? Can the corruptible, and mortall, which never did, nor never ſhall ſee incorruption and immortalitie, make with their corruptible hands, and changeable unrighteous Idolatrous hearts, the reſemblance or likeneſſe of the Incorruptible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>From the Lord God I ſay and declare unto you all, your bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to your Croſſes and Images and Pictures, praying upon Beads, to <hi>Mary,</hi> and Saints, is abomination to the Lord God of Heaven and Earth; and in theſe things you are but a ſtinke to the reſt of the Heathen, who with you doe ſtand Enemies to the Doctrine, Goſpel, and Croſſe of our Lord Jeſus; for as they in words doe hold the name of our Lord in contempt, you with your deceitfull ſhaddowes doe make a mock of truth, and his ſufferings: in loathſomeneſſe you are ſeated, as an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſight of God who created you, and in the eye and ſight of the ſervants of the Lord, who by the price of blood are redeemed, and with pure water are waſhed from the poluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the iniquitie, and the blood and envie which is among you, and the reſt of the Nations, kinreds, tongues, and peoples of the Earth, and now are the followers of the Lambe whether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth. Abundantly do the Scripture beare teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt your practices (mark) from the precepts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God,<note place="margin">Exod: 20.4.</note> unto <hi>Moſes</hi> through the houſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the life of the Saints, ſearch and then ſee;<note place="margin">Iſa: 44.3.</note> might not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60053:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you with as much confidence make a calfe, and ſay to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, this is the reſemblance of God, worſhip ye it; and draw the picture of a Monſter, and ſay, this is the reſemblance of the wonderfull Spirit which was in <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> bowe ye before it.<note place="margin">Read <hi>Jer:</hi> the 23.11, 12, 13, 14, 15 verſes.</note> Oh miſerable blindneſſe, and the greateſt darkneſſe is the Prieſts ignorance, who teach the people lyes, and cauſe them to erre in their wayes. With the light ſearch and ſee how far you are from being under the power of the word of the Lord, who contrary to the letter of the Scriptures, <hi>Do worſhip in the forme of the traditions of your fore-fathers.</hi> Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples in thoſe dayes;<note place="margin">Joh: 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>The houre cometh, and now is, that the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the father, in ſpirit and in truth; for the father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him;</hi> (mark) ſuch as are in the Spirit,<note place="margin">Math: 23.29.</note> having one father, <hi>which is in Heaven,</hi> but ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet in your ſins, and in the fleſh, are the falſe worſhippers, who have many inſtructions, and traditions, and obſervations gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to you according to the wills, as the product of the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conceptions of your many fathers; and now as ye ſhall turne your minds to the light of the Lord Jeſus, which will rip open your hearts, you will finde that rule to be the equall meaſure of your wayes, which will give you a true fight, that you are not in the truth as it is in Jeſus, who is the truth, in whom, and by whom, and through whom, the Prophets writ their propheſies, and the Apoſtles had their utterance, whoſe words do ſtand to the bearing teſtimony againſt your Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous wayes.</p>
            <p>And verily the ſame words which once <hi>Paul</hi> declared upon <hi>Mars hill</hi> unto your fathers,<note place="margin">Acts. 17.22.</note> now turneth upon the heads of you their children.</p>
            <p>Ye men of <hi>Athens,</hi> I perceive that in all things ye are too ſuperſtitious; for as I paſſed through your City, I found an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls Temple, which was abundantly painted with pictures on every ſide within, which was the Inſcription, which I <hi>John</hi> did reade, TO THE UNKNOWN GOD; Which with the bowings of your bodies unto thoſe ſuperſtitions Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Images, ye ignorantly worſhip, Him declare I unto you; <hi>God that made the world and all things therein,</hi> ſeeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, <hi>dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is he worſhipped with mens hands,</hi> by Temples of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60053:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Pictures, or the cuſtomary and traditionall bowings of your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes unto pictures, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he giveth unto all <hi>life and breath,</hi> and all things; and hath made of <hi>his blood</hi> all Nations of men, for to dwell upon all the face of the earth; And hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation, that they ſhould ſeek the Lord, if happily they might feel after him, and find him, though he be not <hi>far from</hi> every one of us.</p>
            <p>For as much then as we are the off-ſpring of God, we ought not to thinke, which if we were come to the life of the ſeed, ye could not then in the leaſt meaſure imagine or thinke, that the Godhead is like unto gold or ſilver, or ſtone graven, or pictures made or drawne by art or mans device: and the times of this Ignorance God winked at, but now commandeth all men eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where to Repent, becauſe his mighty DREADFULL DAY, is at hand, which he hath appointed, wherein he will Judge in righteouſneſſe, the whole world of mankinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carlo Deſſio, Gumene Stephaci,</hi> called Greek Doctors of your people in the City of <hi>Athens,</hi> among whom I was converſant in the power of the Spirit of the Lord, and preached unto you the Everlaſting Goſpel, in croſſe to your wiſdomes, wherefore ye reſiſted my teſtimony, and called me fool, and ſaid, all young men are fooles;<note place="margin">Acts 13.41.</note> In like manner as your fathers the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Epicurians,</hi> &amp; <hi>Stoicks,</hi> called <hi>Paul</hi> babler; do not you ſhew your ſelves herein to be the deſpiſers ſpoken of; What would you have ſaid to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim: 4.12.</note> if he had come unto you even as I came, in doctrine, and Example? And what would you have ſaid to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jere: 1.6, 17, 18.</note> would you have ſaid otherwiſe unto him then you did unto me, if he had come unto you, as in his day he vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited your nature in the <hi>Jewes that ſought to ſlay him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jere: 26.8.</note> And will you ſay alſo that all the young Prophets in the dayes of old were fooles? And when <hi>John</hi> did write unto <hi>young men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh: 2.13, 14.</note> did he then write unto fooles? Will you call ſuch fooles, who knew the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who were ſtrong, and had overcome the wicked one? And are you ſo ignorant, as not to conſider theſe to be the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes, in which God will fulfill the Propheſies of old,<note place="margin">Joel 2.28.</note> 
               <hi>Your old men ſhall dreame dreames, and your young men ſhall ſee viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> for God hath ſaid, that he will powre out his Spirit upon them; and are ye not wicked in your words, to call ſuch fools?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60053:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Conſider this alſo, did not you manifeſt your ſelves to be moſt ignorant, to ſeek for a ſigne and a miracle then from me whom you called fool? Did not that as much manifeſt your perverſe ignorance, as it did your unbeliefe? Wherein you alſo ſhewed your ſelves to be in the ſame nature of that generation, which ſought for a ſigne in the dayes of Chriſt, whom the Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid unto them,<note place="margin">Math: 12.38.</note> that they were <hi>an evill and an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous generation;</hi> yea your ſin is worſe then theirs was, who ſay that you ſee with a better eye then they did, and by ſo much the more it remaines. Are not you the hypocrites, <note place="margin">Math: 16.3.</note>
               <hi>that can diſcerne the face of the skies, but cannot diſcerne the ſignes of the times?</hi> Like as <hi>Jonas</hi> was three dayes and three nights in the Whales belly, and came forth a Preacher of Repentance, Even ſo are the times at hand.<note place="margin">Math: 24.32.</note> 
               <hi>Learne ye therefore the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Figge tree, when his branch is yet tender, and putteth forth leaves, know ye that the Summer is nigh; for as the dayes of Noah were, ſo ſhall alſo the coming of the Lord be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort words, your faith is fathomed, and your hope is comprehended, your fruits gives the teſtimony of you, one cluſter of your grapes were enough to ſhew the nature of your Vine planted in the Mountaines of <hi>Sodome;</hi> the proverb fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes your age, <hi>The fathers have eaten ſower grapes, and the Childrens teeth are ſet on edge;</hi> yet I ſhall alſo further ſhew you, how that as the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſtood in the dayes of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> ſo you do ſtand in the ſame nature, perverſeneſſe, pride and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie, ruling your hearts now, unto whom God ſent <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> to cry againſt, ſaying, Truſt ye not in lying words, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your ſelves,<note place="margin">Jer: 7.4.</note> The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to your fathers the <hi>Athenians, God dwelleth not in Temples made with hands;</hi> Yet you contrary to the Scriptures, do aſſemble your ſelves as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, to worſhip the works of mens hands, and of your own hands, in the Temples which are made with hands, and ſo you walk contrary to the Scriptures of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles; and touching this matter whereof ye ſay, that ye follow the Councell of the Ancient fathers, you who are called the wiſeſt fathers in theſe dayes, ſhew by the beſt teſtimony that ye are able, in what manner you eſteeme the Councell of your Ancient fathers, and how that it is greater,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60053:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ought more to be eſteemed, and followed, then the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of our only father, the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, who gave the utterance of his counſel, thorow <hi>Jeremiah, Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer: 26.12.</note> and others, crying againſt the Temples and againſt your cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, the traditions of your fore-fathers; and Chriſt ſaid, Behold your houſe is left unto you deſolate; and <hi>Paul</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Temples made with hands.</p>
            <p>Where had you or your fathers ever a command from God or, from Chriſt, to build ſuch houſes, and to paint them full of pictures? Conſider and lay it truly to heart ye men through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the earth, is not your building of theſe houſes one, and of the very ſame nature, and the fruits of the very ſame Spirit in thoſe which made the Calfe whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> was with God and not in the Camp amongſt them?<note place="margin">Exod: 32.</note> In the dayes of old upon a much more ſeeming account of aſſured confidence, was the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the <hi>Jewes</hi> of <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> teſtimony then yours poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly can be in theſe latter dayes; for as much as their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had a commandement concerning the Temple, and they might ſay unto <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> who was as a ſtripling, and as it were a childe, Art thou greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> whom God appointed to build us this Temple? Nevertheleſſe, and although <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was as one alone in that work, yet this was his teſtimony, he knew that he was of God,<note place="margin">Jer: 26.15.</note> 
               <hi>Whether they would heare or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare;</hi> and they having corrupted themſelves in a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, he was therefore ſent to cry againſt them, and if they were cryed againſt, as being a people corrupted in a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, how much more thinke ye, ought ye to be born wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and teſtimony againſt, who have contrary to the Word, or any command, abuſed your ſelves, and diſhonoured God, in and through the workes and inventions of your degenerated fore-fathers; much leſſe therefore, could you in your nature receive my teſtimony in the name and power of the Lord, if ye were commanded, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> were, or had any example as they had, ſo ſuitable with their time, ſeeing ye ſleight my teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and do make a mock of my witneſſe, againſt your Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, pictures, bowings, beads, croſſes, and croſſings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for which ye have neither precept, preſident, example, or the leaſt commandement throughout all the Scriptures of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſts words, and the Apoſtles writings, that ever ſuch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60053:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
things were, or ſhould in any age in the Truth come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>What benefit therefore doe you purchaſe to your ſouls, through the exerciſe of your tongues in ſmooth words and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, what advantageth it, if you ſay that you believe in Chriſt, whileſt the words of Chriſt are not a Law unto you? but the traditions of your Fathers ſtand the Law of liberty, for your blind hearts to walk in the crookedneſſe of their ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; What is Chriſt Jeſus unto you, whileſt you forſake his way, life and council, and in enmity thereunto are acting, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping and walking in the way, life, and councils of men of corrupt, and degenerated minds? which you call the faith of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholique Church? what is the Catholique Church, to the Church of Chriſt? ſeeing they have not the word, nor council of Chriſt; And therefore much farther from the work, life, and faithfull order of the doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>You may blind the ſimple, and deceive the ignorant, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſouls of thouſands that know not the right hand from the left; Unto you Doctors I ſpeak, unto whom alſo my words in the Light and Life of the Lord Jeſus is a Riddle and a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; Ye know not the right hand from the left, and therefore I write little things unto you, &amp; do ſpeak plain words concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, that in all your Countreys and Colledges, ye may be no longer the deceived, and deceivers; The deluded, and deluders; The deſtroyed, and deſtroyers; And therefore I further ſay, That it is not a ſhame unto you, whoſe long hairs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares ſeniority without, in the Antiquity of your dayes, to ſtoop and bow your necks, for your backs to bear the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Rod of your younger in years; and know ye that it was prudence in as many of the aged, whoſe faces wore a fair ſhew of grey hairs, not to deſpiſe the youth of tender <hi>Timothy.</hi> And remember that little <hi>David</hi> ſmote and ſlew the great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtine, and the glory was the Lords, and in this alſo I give the praiſe and honour unto God, who is ariſen to ſmite the earth, who alſo hath ſmitten many Iſlands thereof, and his word rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth unto the utmoſt end of the many continents, wherein the Beaſts of the field have an habitation, and the Lord God will hunt the Foxes, and deſtroy the Wolves, and ſlay the Lyons of the Forreſts, which have ſcattered the ſheep of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60053:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Fold, and preyed upon the Heritage of God. Oh earth where are they devourers hid? they have made merry, but they ſhall be vexed; they have ſported, but they ſhall be tormented. Ye men of learning, what is your learning? Ye men of ſtrength, what is your ſtrength? Bring forth your Books, and let us put them in the Ballance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome, Rome,</hi> Hide not thy Daughters, but let the whole earth ſee the Daughters of thy pleaſure, and let us come and reaſon with you a little, to ſee if thy daughters of delight and eaſe, which have been born without pain, are meet to make marriage with the Sons of God, for whoſe birth <hi>Zion</hi> hath tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled: Yea her children, yea all the daughters of your mother <hi>Rome,</hi> plead with your mother, and ſay unto your mother, if thou who haſt born us without travel beeſt not an Harlot, in thy prophane pleaſure, then let us know of a truth, alſo, whether it is not meet that we may be given unto a holy Nation, that a Seed may be preſerved to the praiſe of the name of the Leader of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Oh <hi>Italy</hi> thou haſt a remnant within thee which plague ſhall not touch, although Peſtilence as a Beſom ſhall ſweep thy Land; Repent, if peradventure ye may be ſpared.</p>
            <p>Ye Doctors, I have not yet left you, having alſo publiquely to proclaim Gods controverſie with you; take to you the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of your two Churches, number your Armyes, arme your Hoſts, whet your ſwords, yet behold in the day of battel, God will wound you, when you ſhall not ſmite the Lord. I have ſeen your ſtrength, and have paſſed by your truſt, and at that time the wind of the Lord God did ſhake the earth wherein I walked. What is your Spear to the Arrows of the Lord? Let <hi>Romes</hi> Univerſity anſwer my enquiry. What is your wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers beam unto <hi>Davids</hi> ſmooth ſtones? What are your <hi>Silo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſms</hi> to truth? What is your <hi>Philoſophy</hi> to the Light? What are all your critical Inventions and cunning contrivances, to the word which cannot be changed? You cal'd <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> what are your many colours to white? You Prieſts, what are your changeable Coats, unto that one without a ſeam?</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Athens,</hi> Thy Members are in my remembrance, and ye the Paſtors of the People (mark) your ſheep, yea, your ſheep do bear your own mark. The Lord moved me on the 27. day of the 7. Month, in the year accounted 1657. being the firſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60053:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
day of the week, the day of <hi>Greeks</hi> ſolemn worſhip. Hear this ye Doctors of <hi>Athens,</hi> and Prieſts thereof, who miniſter in the Idols Temples, and Houſe of <hi>Rimmon;</hi> The Lord moved me to read in the place of your ſolemnity, and a witneſſe went with me, to the ſealing of my teſtimony, and at which time, Behold your worſhippers did bow to their pictures, giving forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and laughter in our faces, and I ſaid Gods hand is againſt you, and he that fits in Heaven laughs you to ſcorn. O horrible abomination! Hear this ye Prieſts, mark the fruits of your miniſtry ye Doctors; Behold they declared you in the ſtreet, and ſpread your name in the open places, your Temples could not contain their lightneſs and wickedneſſe, for afterwards in a mock of the Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, even in the ſtreets of your City, the people would meet us, and ſtand openly againſt us, and croſſe themſelves, with many bowings, and much ſcorn and laughter before us; I ſaw the envy of their hearts, and the murder of their minds, who would have dragged us out of your Temple, whileſt the ſecond time in that houſe we bore our teſtimonies againſt your Idolatries, do not theſe in the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their practices plainly preach the doctrine of your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and life? are not theſe the teſtimony of the root of your Miniſtry? are not theſe the fruits of your labours? Oh bluſh! bluſh and be aſhamed of your profeſſion of the name Goſpel, and Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, and of your own name and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among the people, and learn firſt of the loweſt in you, if hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily you may come to ſee the abaſing of that which exalteth it ſelf above all that is called God among you; Ponder it, ponder it in your Cloſets, and ſhut it not out of your ſecret meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and anſwer before the Lord in righteouſneſſe; With what confidence can you preſent your ſelves, or any one of theſe the fruits of your labours in the ſight of God? Can you offer them as an unſpotted ſacrifice in the preſence of the Lord? Will you call theſe Lambs of the Flock? what then are the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the earth begotten by an unnatural ſeed in the womb of a ſtrange Beaſt? Are not theſe your people? and are not you their Doctors, Prieſts, and Prophets? The propheſie is fulfilled,<note place="margin">Hoſea 4.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>They eat up the ſin of my people, and they ſet their heart on their iniquity, and there ſhall be like people, like Prieſt;</hi> Mark this you the Heads of the two Catholique Churches, even unto
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60053:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the tails of your Tribes, you that have received the councils of your ancient Fathers, <hi>The ancient and the honourable he is the Head, and the Prophet that teacheth lyes he is the Tail;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.15, 16.</note> For the Leaders of this people cauſe them to erre, and they that are lead of them are deſtroyed. How long will ye ſtand in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and not underſtand the word of the Lord? Have ye not an ear to hear, nor a heart to underſtand, how that if you had ſtood in the council of the Lord, and cauſed the people to hear his words, and not to have hearkned to the councils of men, who ſtood not in the council of the Lord, then you ſhould have turned them from their evil way, and from the evil of their doings, but becauſe you have hearkned to that council which the Lord did not ſend,<note place="margin">Jer: 23.32.</note> and have taught the people the councils of your Fathers, in the profeſſion of the name of the council of the Lord, which the Lord did not ſend, nor command, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do you not profit the people at all; Behold the people may weigh your lightneſſe, and meaſure your vanity, have you brought forth any other thing then wind? Have not the people heard your preachings and prayings, and partaked of your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and offerings, ſome ten, ſome twenty, thirty, forty, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſixty years, ſome a longer, and others a leſſe time, and yet unto this time, are as much laden with ſin, yea much more preſſed down with iniquity, than in the firſt day that they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taked of your offerings. Is it ignorance that is the ground of your impudence in the practice of your idolatries, or perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that binds the people under your wills, in ſubjection to the affections of your crooked hearts? Are ye void of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the end of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus? Or do ye cover it with iniquity, from the ſight of the eyes of the people? <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle hath written, <note place="margin">Eph: 4.11, 12, 13.</note>
               <hi>Chriſt gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of his body, untill all come in the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt;</hi> And to this end alſo ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> the Scriptures were given forth (which ye hide from the eyes of the people) <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</note>
               <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction. In righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60053:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works,</hi> to which end alſo he preached the myſtery of the Faith,<note place="margin">Col. 1.27, 28.</note> and of the hope of ſalvation, which was <hi>Chriſt in them the hope of Glory, which he that hath this hope in him puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himſelf even as he is pure,</hi> warning every man, and teaching every man, in all wiſdome, that he might <hi>preſent them perfect in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh 3.3.</note> And <hi>John</hi> alſo bare the ſame teſtimony concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Brethren,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.17.</note> wherein, ſaid he, <hi>we have boldneſſe in the day of judgement, becauſe as he is, ſo are we in this preſent world.</hi> Have not you blinded the eyes of the people, and hid theſe things from their underſtandings? not walking in the order of the life of the Saints. <hi>Paul</hi> who renounced the <hi>hidden things of diſhoneſty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.2.</note> did not hide the Scriptures from the ignorant, but <hi>charged by the Lord that his Epiſtle ſhould be read unto all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 5.27.</note> who walked not in craftineſſe, nor handled the word of God deceitfully, but by open manifeſtation of the truth, commended himſelf to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.23.</note> and he <hi>called God to record, that he had not domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the faith of the brethren.</hi> Although you keep your people under your wills as ſlaves, with their faith bound upon your ſleeves, and thus you ſtarve ſouls in ignorance, and deſtroy them in darkneſſe, teaching them to ſay for their Traditions, that it is the faith of the Church, and the Church cannot erre, although you are not the Church of Chriſt, but a maſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and not one unerring Member throughout all your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions; In this manner you make ignorance the ſtaffe of your truſt, in the dominions of your unrighteouſneſſe, and thus you rule in unreaſonableneſſe, this is the complaint of the Lord againſt you;<note place="margin">Hoſea 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>The people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledge; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have hid knowledge, I will therefore reject you, and you ſhall be no Prieſts unto me, ſeeing you have forgotten the Law of God, I will alſo forget your children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give ear, give ear Oh people, and hear the complaint of the Lord againſt <hi>Italy, Greece, Spain, Portugall, Ireland, and France; as a Cage is full of Birds, ſo are their houſes full of deceipt, therefore they are become great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 25.28, 29, 30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>and waxen rich, they are waxen fat, they ſhine, they overpaſſe the deeds of the wicked. Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord? ſhall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch Nations as theſe? A wonderfull horrible thing is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60053:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in their Land, their Prophets propheſie falſly, and their Prieſts bear rule by their means,</hi> (Even them which do lead them, and cauſe them to erre,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.12.</note> and deſtroyeth the way of their path) <hi>and the people love to have it ſo, but what will ye do in the end thereof?</hi> Mark this ye people, <note place="margin">Hoſea 4.9.</note>
               <hi>Behold I will puniſh them for their wayes, and reward them their doings.</hi> You that have already taſted of Gods vengeance, ſhew ye the Cup to your brethren, that if peradventure they may repent, and not taſte of that indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which hath paſſed over your heads, as a ſtream of fury, reaching unto your preſent woe and miſery.</p>
            <p>As concerning the reading of the Scriptures, by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſeverall of your Nations, although it be ſuch unto whom the Prieſts give licence, yet are they not without the limit of the black chain of your Fathers Annotations, whoſe imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions drew Inferences and concluſions, and have alledged con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and meanings to hold forth their opinions, and the draught of their Traditions, through their abuſe and pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures, that as they have brought themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that promiſe, ſo they tye you with themſelves, under the condition thereof, which <hi>John</hi> writes; <note place="margin">Rev. 22.18.</note>
               <hi>For I teſtifie unto every man that hears the words of the Propheſie of this Book, if any man ſhall add unto theſe things, God ſhall add unto him the plagues that are written in this Book.</hi> Under this promiſe and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without controverſie you are holden, who are bound under the frame and faſhion of your fathers conſtructions, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions have the dominion over your faith, and that of God in you hid, under the covert of the product of the iniquity of their life.</p>
            <p>Wherefore all ye ſimple ſouls be awakened, and feel that in you, which with all that ever you have yet heard, your brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſouls are not ſatisfied; in ſecret feel the languiſhing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, which no mans meanings concerning the Scriptures, could fill or preach life unto; Feel your hunger, that you may come to witneſſe the bleſſing unto that ſtate and condition; under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand alſo that if you or your Fathers were in the life of that, by which the Scriptures were ſpoken forth, they could not have written meanings upon them, neither could your eye be turned to read them, or your hearts inclined to receive them, for the Prophets and all the Holy men, they did mean the ſame thing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60053:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which they ſpake, they were far from corruptions in their decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and ſpake not words, but ſuch as were punctually accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their intentions, without any Equivocations; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ye were but in the Life, ye would underſtand the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and ſo your fathers have erred in the order of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, they have begun at the wrong end, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot perfect, or bring you to a good end.</p>
            <p>This principal matter concerning your ſalvation they have neglected, they never touched the feeling part of your heart, whereby the vail thereof ſhould be rent, that you might ſee with your own eye, and hear with your own eare, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with your own heart, but alwayes they bound your ſences in the womb of conception of death, and never brought you forth unto life; and the choyceſt of your Members are but as dead ſtocks and Images, and how could they lead you unto that, where they themſelves never entred? They are not paſſed through the vail which is the fleſh of Chriſt (as <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Brethren, who after the manner of men knew not Chriſt according to the fleſh, ſaith, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.16.</note>
               <hi>Yea although we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet now henceforth know we him no more</hi>) I ſay your Prieſts and Paſtors, they never paſſed through his fleſh to the witneſſing of the true entrance into his body as Members, joyned unto the one Head, which is the new and living way, which Jeſus by the power of his coming,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.20.</note> hath conſecrated for us, who are Redeemed by the purchaſe of his blood (which ſprinkleth our conſciences from every evil and dead word and work) from the world, and the unrighteouſneſſe of their way, then how far ſhort think you, are ye in the life and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice? if your Doctors, Prieſts, Paſtors and Teachers, are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Scriptures, and of the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus and his Croſs, which unto as many as have received is in the true life of the underſtanding of the truth (that is to ſay) the Goſpel of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16. 1 Cor. 1.18.</note> and the Croſſe of the Lord Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>is the power of God unto ſalvation,</hi> which if they were Miniſters of the true Church, and you Members alſo thereof, then would you be all in one Life (to wit) <hi>in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14.6.</note> who is <hi>the Life,</hi> which if you were in Chriſt who is the Life, then need you not another thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Life to confirm your underſtandings in the reading of the Scriptures, which by the Life were given forth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60053:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Can your nations therefore look a little way before you? that you may conſider it in your hearts, and ponder it ſoberly in your ſecret meditations; however, I know the Heathen will kick againſt, and the high obſtinate-hearted will deſperately reſiſt, even ſuch in whole ſight, the ſoules of the ſimple are not of any account, neither the glory of the Lord their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, whoſe praiſe through criticall Arguments, and Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, is in gaining dominion, and obtaining ſuch maſtery, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make a boaſt of their vaine victory; yet there is a ſeed, which can receive my teſtimony, which is the Remnant of the Lord, which under the iniquities of your Leaders, hath been held in <hi>Egypt,</hi> under miſerable bondage, and cruell captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; I ſay, look a little way before you, with diligence into that which I write concerning you.</p>
            <p>You are not come unto the life of the firſt principle, which leads to the underſtanding, and knowledge of the oracles and myſteries of God, and of his kingdome of ſalvation, and ſo are farre ſhort of receiving, partaking, and enjoying of the pure life and power of the Spirit of life, in the power and the life in your hearts, which in the particular unto every true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church of Chriſt Jeſus gives the infallible witneſſe and teſtimony, that they are born of the undefiled wombe, and incorruptible ſeed of promiſe, unto life everlaſting; By which alſo the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus was preached <hi>to the Spirits in priſon,</hi> and the Scriptures and Propheſies of old,<note place="margin">1 Pet: 3.19.</note> were given forth and ſpoken, <note place="margin">2 Pet: 1.21.</note>
               <hi>which came not by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt;</hi> Which no minde nor heart of man, or underſtanding of mankinde, without the ſame Spirit can read aright; No lyar, ſwearer, proud, envious, thiefe, covetous, nor Idolater, ungodly or prophane perſon can read them, except their own portions from them <note place="margin">Mal: 4.1. Pſal: 9.17.</note>
               <hi>(viz.) The lake is the portion of the lyar, the proud ſhall be as ſtubble in the day of the Lord, and the wicked ſhall be turned into hell;</hi> But every member according to the diverſities of their meaſures of the Spirit of life, who are of the true Church, can witneſſe, and read the Scriptures, with the life, in their life, <hi>which is hid with Chriſt in God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col: 3.3.</note> but you ſtanding only in that which hath written Annotations, and which draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Inferences, Concluſions, and meanings from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60053:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that witneſſeth ſufficiently concerning you, that you are not in the life of the firſt Principle of pure Religion, which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the underſtanding of the Scriptures; Ignorance therefore is the cauſe of your error,<note place="margin">Math: 22.29. Math: 13.34.</note> as ſaith Chriſt, <hi>You erre not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God;</hi> Wherefore unto you they are parables and hidden ſentences from the darkneſſe of your clouded underſtandings; who is he that ſeeth your miſery, and doth not lament you? who have conſented to the blinding of your ſelves, through the yeelding of your minds captives to the perverſe wills of your Inſtructers, they have trodden out paths in unrighteouſneſſe, and you have walked in their croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: Verily, I am as one wounded for your ſakes, and heavily preſſed with the clods which the ploughers have ploughed upon your backs. Oh where is the hand which hath holpen you? Have not your watchers forgiven you your ſins in vanitie, and ſtrengthened your hands, with the ſtrength of their own hearts in iniquitie? In what manner have they brought you unto confeſſion, and what will that availe you, if after your confeſſions, the ſame and worſe ſins and iniquities are wrought and committed by you? Are you ſo ignorant, as to thinke that their words of abſolution, is the covenant of pardon and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Or do you thinke that bare confeſſion of your ſins only, will bring you under the Condition of mercy? Mark the order of the declaration of <hi>Solomon's</hi> wiſe ſentence, which maketh fruſtrate the expectation of your vaine confidence;<note place="margin">Pro: 28.13.</note> 
               <hi>He that covereth his ſins ſhall not proſper, but who ſo confeſſeth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh them ſhall finde mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh people, why therefore will ye thus reſt, and remaine in the night of ſlumber? when will ye be awakened, to come to ſee the works of your teachers? how that they have double-girded your loynes with the cords of ignorance, and have made that the ſtrength of their renowne and praiſe in the Nations, and your cloathing with the clouds of darkneſſe is your Prieſts garment of glory over you, by this their power governes in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Majeſty, and you remaine as Subjects, chained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoak of their iniquitie; Oh who can declare your miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? It is my ſorrow for the Seeds ſake to behold it, and I know that it ſuits not with the delight of your hearts, to read the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of it; But hath the Lord a Remnant, and ſhall he not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60053:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
viſit for the ſake thereof? yea verily, and this therefore in love to the ſoules of the ſimple, that they may come to the light of the day, each one in the ſenſibleneſſe of his own heart and life, to reade with underſtanding the myſtery of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Scriptures of truth, which do ſpeak one and the ſame thing, in the word and intention, and not of many things, as by more then one, but of all things in and by one, through whom the worlds were made, and the Covenant of God ſtands ſure, through whom alſo grace, mercy and peace is come to as many as are joyned to that one, in the clearneſſe of the naked truth, through the relinquiſhing of the hidden things of deceit, and all the former wayes, vanities, cuſtomes, traditions, ſuperſtitions, and ungodly words and works, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the counſells of the many fathers and men of the world, (through the ſpreading of whoſe ſpirit, and the fruits of their life, deluſion hath a long time reigned in the world,) cleaving to the only ſound counſell of the living God, &amp; father of truth, which deceiveth nor deludeth any man, but eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all men that come unto it in a holy way, exceeding the errors of mans wayes, even in that <hi>new and living way,</hi> which he hath prepared, <hi>wherein the uncleane cannot walke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa: 55.8.</note> but it is unto thoſe, <hi>the way-faring men, though foales, ſhall not erre therein.</hi> Wherefore all people be not any longer blinded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the perverſe crooked wills of your Inſtructers and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, but examine and try truly, whether they have lead you in the way of God, wherein the wicked cannot walke. And now in all this will you count me your enemy, in putting you upon diligent inquiry, and alſo in telling you the truth? Lay it to heart oh people, and you Doctors and Teachers of the Nations, Come forth and conſider, aſſemble, aſſemble the principal members of your bodyes together, and call a full Councell of the Magicians of your Lands, and ſuffer us then to prove you before all men; provide your rods, that you may caſt them in the preſence of the Nations, and behold ours is ready to be caſt alſo, that it may be knowne, whether God is the God of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that all the Inhabitants of the Earth may have an underſtanding, who are the people that have ſtolen the name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were never borne of his Seed; and if it ſhall be ſeene that the <hi>Serpent</hi> of our rod,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60053:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhall eate up the <hi>Serpents</hi> of your rods, then of a truth it ſhall be knowne that God worketh with us, and not with you, but againſt you; But if the <hi>Serpent</hi> of our rod ſhall be ſwallowed up, and by the <hi>Serpents</hi> of your rods utterly devoured, then let not the Nations ſpare to publiſh, and cry in their ſtreets, that the God whom we worſhip hath utterly forſaken us.</p>
            <p>Againe, I ſay aſſemble your Prophets, and let the worke of the Lord, and his word <hi>anſwering by fire</hi> give teſtimony to the Prophets, whether the Prophets of your Lands, are the true Prophets, that the Inhabitants thereof may truly know and underſtand, that if the Lord be God, then let them follow him, but if <hi>Baal</hi> whom ye worſhip he God, then do you continue following of him, no hurt will come unto your Nations through the tryall of the Prophets; ſo that if the Lord anſwers our Prophet by fire, and kindles the ſacrifice of the oblation in your ſight, then ſhall ye know that our Prophet is the true Prophet of the Lord; but if your Prophets ſhall cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, even to the drawing of blood of their bodyes, and no word of anſwer to their ſupplications, as the anſwer of the Lord by fire from Heaven; but afterwards, if in their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and wilfulneſſe they ſhall kindle a fire in their wrath, and charge you to kindle fires in your houſes to burne this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, among whomſoever it comes, then behold that ſhall be a ſigne unto you, that God is not among them; for if the Lord be their God, then would he plead for them, or if they be Jealous for the Name of the Lord God of Hoſts, then will they ſtand forth, to plead the word of the Lord, upon the Mount of the Lord, in the face of all the Nations of the earth; Oh people, let this be a teſtimony unto you, either for you, or againſt you, that either your Prieſts and Prophets have decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you, in prophecying and declaring ſmooth things unto you, or that they have alwayes taught you Righteouſneſſe, and inſtructed you in the Everlaſting Precepts of the undefiled, and un-erring path of truth and holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Heare therefore this ye Prieſts, and give eare ye Teachers of the people, hide not, hide not your faces, but come forth, come forth, that we may try the feeding of your Paſtures, that the blinde may feele with what they are laden; Have not they given a price for wheate? and have not you laden them with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60053:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ſtubble of the reaped and gleaned fields, and the chaffe of the wheate? Was not the price of their money for the cleare running water of the Rock; and have not ye fill'd their veſſells with the ſetled lees of your own Ciſterns? Behold, I have ſeen the deep workes of your hands, even the deep wells which ye have digged with your own hands, and the breadth, length, heighth, and depth thereof I have meaſured, and the foundations thereof I have diſcovered; You Doctors of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> Remember my rod, which touched your bottome, wherewith your dreggs were ſtirred up, which caſt a ſtinke in my noſtrills, at which time ye could ſcarce cover your loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe, in the preſence of your Diſciples; I have not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſtrength on which you took hold, which appeared and proved as a ravelled String of a broken Bow, which could not carry forth ſo as to ſend home the ſhaft; You aymed at my birth, to have trodden upon the ſimplicitie and tenderneſſe of my youth, yet could not your broken ſpeares reach to the hurt of my life. Now therefore ſearch ye further, even unto the uttermoſt end of the Records of your Books, to finde out the firſt day of my life, which although I am (after the account of the manner of men) but as a ſeed of the ſecond or third ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of this age brought forth, yet never the leſſer is mine age (in a juſt account more ancient and honourable, then the dayes of your birth; your age muſt yet be borne unto Infancy, if ever you come to the poſſeſſion of the promiſe of Gods E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting kingdome, and the glory of your Antiquitie muſt come unto great contempt; and your eyes and your hearts which have boaſted in vanitie, muſt paſſe through the flames of the conſuming fire of Gods Jealouſie, before ye ſhall enter the Paradiſe which you made a mock of in ignorance, and ſo bare witneſſe unto the curſe of your kingdome, as a people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the ground, where bleſſing hath not raiſed the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the earth. Furthermore, heare this ye Prieſts, Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and Inſtructers of the people; The cry of the earth is grievous in the eare of the Lord againſt you, <hi>blood hath touched blood</hi> in your Lands, the ſoules of the ſimple have uttered their groanes through the creviſſes of the graves, the ſlaughters in your Cities, and the murders in your ſtreets, the blood which plague hath devoured, and which famine and drought hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60053:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
even for theſe, and more then theſe, the earth lifts up her voyce againſt you; Have not you caſt away the bread, and given ſtones to the children? Have not you eaten the uncleane fiſh, and ſpued out Serpents in the faces of the daughters? Oh how many are the thouſands of thouſands, whom you have cauſed to erre, and which have periſhed through your lyes and lightneſſe; and will not God avenge himſelfe on the heads of his enemies? As ye have gloried in the dayes of your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and made your ſelves fat with the joy of your laughter and wantonneſſe, even ſo ſhall Gods time of viſitation be as a ſnare unto your life in unrighteouſneſſe, even as a ſnare unto the Prieſt, and a ginne unto the Prophets, and as a trap, and cleane Inſtrument, to take hold of the heads of the Churches of your Nations, yet ſhall it end as the houre of Everlaſting mercies, if ye Repent; which if ye reſiſt, behold time ſhall not bring end to your torment, when God ſhall ſtretch your bodyes upon the bed of endleſſe trouble and miſery.</p>
            <p>A warning therefore, and a word of Awakening, even the utterance of life ſounding through your black doores of the darkneſſe of death; to you Prieſts, <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Patriarke,</hi> of the Lands, who ſay that you ſit in <hi>Peters</hi> ſeate, to pardon the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of the people, and to forgive them their ſinnes, and to binde and to looſe things anſwerable to your pleaſures on earth, ſaying, that <hi>this is your Authoritie, in the place and roome of the Diſciples, according to the Scriptures,</hi> Joh: 20.23. Math: 16.19.</p>
            <p>It is not the ſeede, nor the off-ſpring of your roote, but the children of another generation, which in the nature of the life of the holy Apoſtles are their true ſucceſſors; you are deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearts, and wicked ſinners; you are men in the fleſh, and your bodyes are lumps of ſinfull fleſh; your generation is of the wombe and ſeed of corruption, and your life in the changable nature; heare ye therefore, God never gave his Everlaſting Authoritie of Righteouſneſſe for the Remiſſion of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Joh: 20.22.</note> unto deceitfull hearts, and ſinners: Chriſt <hi>breathed</hi> on his Diſciples, and gave them the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> by which breath, even by the vertue thereof, and the power of the gift of the Holy Ghoſt their Authority ſtood in the worke and will of the Lord; But Chriſt on you, nor on your <hi>Pope,</hi> or <hi>Patriarke,</hi> hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60053:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not in this manner breathed, nor in like manner filled either you or them with the Holy Ghoſt; and therefore being without the true virtue, and effectual authority, you ſit but as deceitful ſhadows and Images, in your wicked, wilful, preſumptuous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances, making a reall mock of the true power and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; Oh how preſumptuous are you in your abominable works of iniquity, and as a people ſetled in the hardneſſe of the ground of your fore-fathers Apoſtacy? I have already ſhewed your root,<note place="margin">Dan 9.9.</note> how in the degeneration you are departed from the Rock, which in all ages was the ground of the forgiveneſſe of ſins, which unto the Lord only belongs,<note place="margin">Acts 5.31.</note> and Chriſt only is this day the Prince and Saviour, granting unto his people, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſalvation, and forgiveneſſe of ſins,<note place="margin">Eph: 1.7.</note> and this was <hi>Pauls</hi> teſtimony to the <hi>Epheſians, In whom we have redemption through his blood,</hi> (Mark the order of <hi>Pauls</hi> witneſſe, the redemption through the waſhing of his blood, goeth before) the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſins <hi>according to the riches of his grace,</hi> (Read this ye people) according to the riches of his grace, how then is it of works, or by the words of your ſinfull <hi>Pope, Patriarch,</hi> and Prieſts, and Teachers?</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore ye have turned the riches of the grace of Chriſt Jeſus into an abominable habit of blind ſhews of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, deluding the people, and deceiving the hearts of the ſimple. Awake, awake to the judgement, Behold the breath of the holy Apoſtles life, is ready to utter voices in the earth, as thunders againſt you, deſtruction to your dwellings, deſolation to your habitations. I have ſeen a dart within your doores which will wound you, and when the day of God as a Thief in the night overtakes you, Remember ye were war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto repentance, that you might eſcape <hi>the floods which ſhall overwhelm your Lands, unto the determination of the conſummation, and decree of everlaſting indignation and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And furthermore ye Prieſts, who ſay that you officiate as <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors, in the degree and order of your places, I have both ſeen you, your fruits, and your labours, and that hath plainly declared in the ſubſtance unto me, that you have not the leaſt relation unto the life of <hi>Peter,</hi> being but the dirt and duſt which the upright and undefiled ſpirit of <hi>Peter</hi> ſhakes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60053:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
from off his feet, as a witneſſe againſt your Cityes and habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even in this day, as a witneſſe againſt the wickedneſſe and Idolatries of your Generation; and whilſt you are profeſſing <hi>Peter's</hi> power and authority, of binding and looſing on earth, your manifold deceits hath blinded your hearts, whereby you are ſo much ignorant of the word and work of Gods power, that your corrupt wiſdomes exerciſed in ſtudies to the end of your evill dayes, ſhall never find out the earth, wherein the juſt life of <hi>Peter</hi> is this day entred, binding the unrighteouſneſs of your life and ſpirits, under him as his Foot-ſtool, everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to tread and trample upon the glory of your heads, and crown of your deceits.</p>
            <p>Oh ye <hi>Greek</hi> Paſtors, Prieſts and people, what can you plead for your Patriarch? Can you not read the deceitfulneſſe of his ſucceſſion, through the manner of his Election? Dare you ſay that it is according to the election of the grace of Chriſt Jeſus, in the order of the truth, or power of the true Faith? who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of Life, and doctrine of the true faith, doth purchaſe unto himſelf that Title and Degree, with the price of a ſum of moneys, from the <hi>Emperour</hi> of the <hi>Turks,</hi> whom you your ſelves do ſay is Antichriſt, and Reprobate concerning the faith of Chriſt, an enemy to the life of the Saints and ſpirit of <hi>Peter,</hi> of whom you ſay that your <hi>Patriarch</hi> is his ſucceſſor: Oh confeſſe, confeſſe your blindneſs, and bluſh, bluſh and be aſhamed of your impudence, and obſtinacy in ignorance; for behold if your foundation and root concerning the remiſſion of your ſins be rotten, what farther prop or poſt to your ſelves can you hew out in your imaginations and inventions, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the deceived walls of your Fathers buildings.</p>
            <p>And again, After one hath paid the price, for the purchaſe of his Office, if another of your Nation goes with his ſum of moneys and gives to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> he diſpoſſes the firſt, and gives the Degree and Title to the latter; Oh horrible abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, who hath a voice and hath with-holden, and not cryed in the ſtreets, and publiſhed it in the open places, even the iniquity and the abomination, and not cryed againſt the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe thereof, by ſuch deſperate mockings of God, through the wickedneſſe of their purchaſes? Read diligently the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.19, 20, 21. <hi>But Peter ſaid unto him, thy money
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60053:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money. Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter, for thy heart is not right in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> Now compare the practices and ſee, if the unrighteouſneſſe of <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer who was in the gall of bitterneſs, doth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel the ſtrength of the ſealed bonds of iniquity of your <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs</hi> Succeſſors; and finally touching this matter, take this as the ſumme to your ſelves, the original and ground of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable granting, and your receiving the remiſſion of ſin ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth of the reckoning of your own account, is the Reprobate ſpirit of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Read alſo, O <hi>Italy, France, Ireland, Spain and Portugall,</hi> the ſeat of your Father the <hi>Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 18.36.</note> he ſits <hi>exalted in the Kingdom of this world,</hi> contrary to Chriſts example, as King upon the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt mountain, <hi>over many waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 17.15. Matth. 4.8, 9.</note> in the poſſeſſion of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the promiſe of Satan, <hi>All theſe will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me.</hi> The aboundance of his corrupt honour and vain glory, with the abominable fruits of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of his children, and the Prieſts actions in iniquity gives teſtimony of the oath of the witneſſe, that he ſtands principall in the ground of Apoſtacy;<note place="margin">Heſter 3.8, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Hamans</hi> decree which he got granted for the ſlaughter of the Jews, and his Gallows of <hi>fifty cubits high,</hi> which was prepared for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> is the figure of your Fathers <hi>Inquiſitions,</hi> for the taking away the liberty,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.13, 14.</note> and the deſtruction of the life of ſuch as God ſends to declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Traditional worſhips in Superſtition and Idolatry.<note place="margin">Math. 11.29.</note> How far is his life from Chriſts doctrine and example of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? who in the pride of his heart, ſitting on high in the ſeat and Throne of arrogancy, maketh the comers to ſee his face, to fall down before him upon their knees to kiſs his foot? The abomination and loathſomneſſe of the nature of theſe few fruits are ſufficient unto all that have the true ſences of ſeeing and ſavouring, that his ſucceſſion is not in the Covenant of grace, according to the election of God, whom men in the fleſh have elected and choſen unto the glory of the kingdomes of men in this preſent evil world. And finally touching the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of your conceptions, and the deceitfulneſſe of the <hi>Popes</hi> practices, this is the ſum of the account of the true record, concerning the abſolutions and forgiveneſſe of ſins, which ye
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60053:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
receive from his authorized ſons, Your Fathers the Prieſts, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi> which ſought a ſeat above <hi>the meek Prince of ſalvation,</hi> is the root and ground of the iſſues of their grant and warrant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,<note place="margin">Zach: 9.9. Math. 21.5. Iſa: 14.12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</note> whoſe figure and reſemblance is the <hi>revelation of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> He that hath an ear to hear let him hear, and a heart to fear, let him fear.</p>
            <p>I have not in every particular remonſtrated your Traditions and cuſtomes, wherein you walk contrary to the truth, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the teſtimony, ſhall in ſhort ſhew you how that you are ſhort of the ſubſtance, in which the promiſe is <hi>yea and amen</hi> of eternall life.</p>
            <p>Your hearts and minds are not ſingly and ſimply joyned to the <hi>Light</hi> of the Lord Chriſt Jeſus, which ſhines in all your conſciences, and thats the cauſe of the foot-ſteps of your wayes, and the birth of your words and works, to proceed and flow forth as the fruits of the womb of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>And in how much in all your wayes, words and works, you are ſhort of the Life, of the Light wherewith you are lightned, even by ſo much you are ſhort of the true way of the Kingdom of God;<note place="margin">John 14.6. John 8.12. John 1.9.</note> For be it known unto you of a truth, <hi>That the way is but one, the truth is but one, and that one is Chriſt the Light of the world, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.4, 5, 6. 1 John 1.5. James 1.17.</note>Wherefore be ye not ignorant, that there is only <hi>one true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, one ſpirit, one hope of the true calling, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, and one communion of the Lords body, one God who is Light,</hi> the eternal Father of all who are children born of the Light, wherewith they are lighted (which cometh from God the Father of Light) unto life everlaſting. This then is the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the whole world, and the meſſage to the whole world, and the tryal of the whole world, their wayes, their words, their works, and their worſhips; all whoſe deeds are wrought in the Light, they in the Light have peace, and their hearts doth not condemn them, but ſuch who profeſſe God and the Truth in Chriſtianity, and yet are Swearers, and Lyars, Thieves, Whores, Whoremongers, Cheaters, Covetous, Proud, Envious, Hard-hearted, Mockers, Scorners, Drunkards, Gluttons, Abuſers of themſelves with mankind, who in worſe nature than the beaſts nature, change the naturall uſe of the creature into that which is againſt nature, theſe walking, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60053:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and acting contrary to the <hi>Light</hi> in all their conſciences, with the Light are judged and condemned, and this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of all the wicked world,<note place="margin">John 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>That Light is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather than Light becauſe their deeds are evill;</hi> And ſuch are not an honour unto God, nor a praiſe unto Chriſt, whoſe life ſavours not of the Truth, nor of the nature of Chriſtianity; their profeſſion ſhall in no wiſe be unto their Juſtification; But in how much they have profeſſed the name of Chriſt who is the Light, and made the profeſſion of his name the Cloak of their unrighteouſneſſe; even by ſo much the more, will the Light in all their conſciences be the aggravation of their miſery, through judgement unto condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Unto this one therefore muſt all come to be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the everlaſting inheritance of ſalvation, even unto the <hi>Light</hi> which cometh from Chriſt, by it to be led unto Chriſt, who <hi>is the Life and Light of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1.4. Iſa: 42.6. Iſa: 49.6. Luke 2.32.</note> who is the ſalvation of the Prophets, whom they propheſied of, ſaying, <hi>I will alſo give thee for a Covenant of the people, for a Light of the Gentiles, to open the eyes of the blind, to bring out the Priſoners from the Priſon, and them that ſit in darkneſſe out of the Priſon houſe, that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation to the ends of the earth;</hi> On whom alſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles believed, who through Faith in the Light, and obedience to the Light, wherewith they were lightned, were made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the purchaſe of the blood, and promiſe of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (to wit) the ſalvation of their ſouls: And behold this is the Enſign and Standard of the Lord, which was ſet up for the fall and is now ſetting and ſet up for the riſing again of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in <note place="margin">Luke 32.34, 35.</note>
               <hi>Iſrael, and for a ſign which ſhall be ſpoken againſt, by whom ſhall come the revelation and ripping open of all thoughts and hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye people all upon the face of the whole earth, unto that in all your conſciences, which revealeth unto you all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the prophaneſſe, and rottenneſſe of your own hearts, and the wickedneſſe of your own thoughts, words, and works, which alſo is the revelation of the terrible indignation, and of the wrath of God againſt all the ungodly, and workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, even unto that light in all your conſciences, muſt ye all be joyned, your hearts muſt be given unto it, to be led and to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60053:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
be ordered, and guided by it, that you may come to witneſſe a new Life, begotten by the Light in you, <note place="margin">John 3.3.</note>
               <hi>for except a man be born again, he cannot ſee, nor enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As your minds come therefore to be joyned to the Light, wherewith you are lightned, you by the witneſs of perfect ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and obedience to the pure motions of it, will come to know the true and everlaſting teſtimony of the Lord, and be made partakers of the hope of the heavenly calling, and your confidence (not as in the dayes of vanity, ſin, and death) will be gathered into the one ſubſtance of the ſpirit of Life, in which you will come to ſee what is the glory of the living body, which liveth by the faith of the Son of God; Your baptiſme will not be as in the dayes under the power of the Elements; For as much as the Teſtimony of the life of Jeſus is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of Scriptures. <hi>John</hi> he ſaid that Chriſt who was the ſubſtance ſhould <hi>increaſe,</hi> but he who baptized with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as the figure) ſhould <hi>decreaſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 3.11.</note> ſignifying alſo the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Chriſt, that it ſhould be with <hi>fire and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which he teſtified concerning him,<note place="margin">John 1.26, 27.</note> of whom he ſaid, <hi>There ſtandeth one among you of whom ye know not, he it is who cometh after me is preferred before me;</hi> the ſame alſo is he which hath been in the world,<note place="margin">John 1.11.</note> as a ſtranger upon the earth, <hi>who came unto his own, but his own received him not,</hi> whoſe life is manifeſt through the Revelation of the light, wherewith the whole world is lightned, which leadeth unto the knowledge, and witneſſe of his Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Eph: 4.5.</note> Croſſe, Death, Reſurrection, Life, and Communion of his eternal body; and this is the baptiſme which the Apoſtle teſtified, is only <hi>One,</hi> even the baptiſme of the Holy Ghoſt, and with fire, which <hi>John</hi> ſaid ſhould encreaſe through the decreaſe of the water; Fleſh and blood revealeth none of theſe things concerning the Kingdome of God, which is a myſtery unto all the world; how great therefore is the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the world, to adminiſter thoſe things which they call Ordinances unto Infants, which things are Parables, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether hidden things in the ſubſtance, from the wiſdome of the world? which if the Revelation and Life of the ſubſtance be not unto the elder, what profiteth then the Traditional waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or ſprinklings, which neither is by commandement or manifeſt example in the Scriptures, unto the infancy of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60053:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
younger? and what can their Infancy through the figures reach, fathom, or feel concerning the ſubſtance, let the worlds Fathers anſwer this for them.</p>
            <p>Unto the croſſe therefore of the Lord Chriſt Jeſus ye ought to come, which neither is gold, nor ſilver, nor braſſe, nor iron, nor any other mettal, nor wood, nor ſtone, nor Image of bone, or any other dead creature; but this is the everlaſting teſtimony of the Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, <note place="margin">Luke 22.42.</note>
               <hi>Father not my will, but thy will be done;</hi> he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear, and he that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not, nor knoweth this, is yet under his own <hi>hour and power of darkneſſe;</hi> Underſtand therefore that the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the will of God is in and through the Light, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you are lightned which cometh from Chriſt the true light of the world, which lightneth every man that cometh into the world, unto which Light in all your conſciences your minds muſt be ſubject, you muſt wait upon God with your minds in the Light, your hearts turned to it, that you may witneſſe the power of it ruling and reigning in you, and working through every Member of your mortal bodies, bringing your wils under it, and ſubduing and ſubjecting your affections to it; this is the true Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, to take up the Croſſe, and to walk in Croſſe unto your wills and affections, which take up Images, and take delight and pleaſure in Pictures, and imaginary like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, and to walk as quickned Members in croſſe to your whole life, as it now ſtands in the nature and luſt of uncleanneſs, ſin and death, in the enmity to the Life and power of God, and myſtery of Godlineſſe, in croſſe to your fooliſh, airy, childiſh, vanities, of Beads, Bracelets, and other Traditional Superſtitions and Idolatries, which things are but the ſignification of folly and childiſhneſſe in the firſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which receiveth not the knowledge nor things of God; the Light alſo wherewith you are lightned,<note place="margin">Eph: 5.4.</note> muſt guide your minds, and ſtay your hearts and thoughts upon God, and lead you alſo in croſſe unto the Lightneſs and wickedneſs of your lives, which ſtand in the pleaſure of vain jeſting and idle foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh talking, <note place="margin">Rom. 13 13.</note>
               <hi>in ſurfeiting and drunkenneſſe, in chambering and wantonneſſe, ſtrife and envying,</hi> in the ground of all manner of ſin, iniquity and miſchief, which produces and yields the fruits of lying, ſwearing, pride, covetouſneſs, cheating and defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60053:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
adulteries, and whoredomes, diſſimulation, robberies, and deſperate murders, even in that evill and curſed ground where man is droven from the preſence of God, under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the agreement of Hell and death, alienated and eſtranged from the Covenant of Life, yoaked under blindneſs, and chay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the blackneſs of darkneſs, ſhut out of the Garden of pleaſure, and Paradice of God, where nothing can reſtore the loſſe which came by tranſgreſſion, but the power of the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, which worketh death to the diſobedient and carnall; There is none other entrance now unto the tree of Life (which he that eateth not thereof dyeth in, and periſheth unto everlaſting death) but through the <hi>flaming ſword,</hi> which is ſet at <hi>Edens</hi> gates,<note place="margin">Gen: 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>to keep the way of the Tree life;</hi> Can your eye read, or your ear hear, for your hearts to receive this ye vain ſcoffers at the Saints entrance into the holy City, and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God? You are witneſſes to your ſelves that your Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is not in the Kingdome of Heaven, which is <hi>like unto a grain of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math: 13.31.</note> which alſo is likened unto an <hi>Onion</hi> ſeed, whoſe perfect fruit being taken out of the natural earth, yet quickly periſheth not, but proſpereth, yielding growth from the body of the root more than all roots of the earth; This is the work of Life, the Croſs, which neither is likeneſs, imitation nor Image of the things, or nature of death, but the mighty power of God, which bringeth death unto death, which hath paſſed over all men,<note place="margin">Rom: 5.10, 12.</note> and reigneth over all men from <hi>Adam</hi> unto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> even over all that have ſinned, who have not known <hi>Moſes,</hi> although their ſin hath not been after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, from loſt <hi>Adam</hi> therefore unto <hi>Moſes</hi> you muſt come, to witneſs an entrance into <hi>Moſes</hi> his houſe, in whom was revealed the hope of the promiſe, that ſhould come to paſſe, which alſo is come in power,<note place="margin">Rom: 8.4.</note> in the ſubſtance to them, <hi>In whom the righteouſneſſe of the Law is fulfilled, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> who have ſeen the Prophets day, and are come through the work of <hi>Johns</hi> cry in the wilderneſs,<note place="margin">Math: 3.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> who are no more of the fleſh, as in the fleſh working the works of the fleſh, but through the death of the Croſſe, are buried in the ſeparation from the worſhips, words and works of the firſt nature, riſen and born unto Life, unto the inheritance of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Juſtification, into the unchangeable Kingdome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60053:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the word of the Covenant, where he that is leaſt, is greater then <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math: 11.11.</note> who was the greateſt Prophet borne of women; and thus being paſſed and tranſlated from death to life, (not as any longer under the power of ſin, are partakers of the Elements, or ſubject unto the carnall Ordinances) are altogether under, and one with the power of the miniſtration of life, in the communion of the Eternall body of the Lord, and from your ſuperſtitions and Images, and nature of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and tranſgreſſion, by the power of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ye muſt be changed through obedience to the motions of the <hi>Light</hi> in all your conſciences into the Image of the glory of the <hi>ſecond Adam, who is the Lord from Heaven,</hi> if ever ye ſhall come to witneſſe a hope which will not wither, to be Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto the heireſhip of the promiſe of the Inheritance of the kingdome, which Covenant was made only with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and with the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> born of the <hi>free-Woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen: 22.16.</note> which by the one Everlaſting <hi>Oath of God</hi> is confirmed unto all that by the <hi>blood of ſprinkling</hi> are entered <hi>into the City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb: 12.22. Rev: 22.15.</note> where not any thing that is defiled can come, for without is the curſe, even over as many as ſtand in the ground without the compaſſe of the fence of the <hi>Paradice of God,</hi> where are dogs, and ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and whore-mongers, and murderers, and Idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lye.</p>
            <p>Repent, Repent therefore, the mighty day of the Lord God is at hand, wherein he will ſift the Nations as with the five of equitie, and fanne the Inhabitants of the earth with the winde of his wrath, and through all Nations will make an equall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration in Righteouſneſſe, the Chaffe from the Wheate, the Droſſe and Reprobate from the refined Silver, the juſt from the vile, him that feareth God from him that feareth him not; A day of woe to the wicked, and of vengeance to the workers of iniquitie; in which cometh to paſſe the Revelation of the Wrath and Indignation of God, which is even ready to be revealed <hi>in flames of burning fire</hi> againſt all the ungodly; A day of howling to the ſonnes of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and of everlaſting lamentation to the daughters of <hi>Gomorrha;</hi> Strength ſhall not defend you, nor Art deliver you, where then will you run for a refuge, ye want the wings of the Sunne of the Morning, to fly unto the ends of the earth, the rockes will not rend to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60053:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you, nor the mountaines move to hide you, ſo terrible is the day of the dreadfull Lord God of Hoſts, and none like it, that even his breath ſhall ſhake terribly the foundations of the earth, and the Iſles of the Sea ſhall role as ſhips in a tempeſt, the Jealouſie of the heavens ſhall ſend forth their winds, which ſhall ſtirre up the depth of the Sea, and ſhe ſhall ſpue out of her wombe, the dead bodyes which her rage devoured upon the earth, alſo the grave ſhall give up her dead, that all both great and ſmall may ariſe, and ſtand before the great Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord; The trumpet of the Lord hath ſounded, and is ſounding; Bleſſed is he that heareth the proclamation of the voyce of the Angel unto the witneſſe, and have a right, and a part in the <hi>firſt Reſurrection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev: 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>on him the ſecond death ſhall have no power, but ſuch ſhall reigne with Chriſt a thouſand yeares,</hi> whoſe day is begun in the earth; he that hath an eare let him heare what the Spirit ſaith; and when the thouſand yeares are finiſhed,<note place="margin">Rev: 20.9.</note> the whole number of the deceivers of the earth ſhall be utterly devoured with the fire of God out of Heaven: A dreadfull found to the wicked I have heard, the proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the voyce of the Archangel of God, and the noyſe of a Joyfull ſhout from Heaven, of which I <hi>John</hi> beare witneſſe, and do hold the teſtimony as unto the witneſſe of the Eternall Decree of God, concerning that which was, and is, and of the Judgement which ſhall come &amp; overtake the wicked, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the mountaines, and the hills, and the caves, and the dens of the earth; woe ſhall compaſſe their dwellings, and Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Wrath ſhall be placed as the bounds of their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; who can count the ſands which are ſet for the bounds of the Seas, he alſo can comprehend the miſery of the workers of iniquitie; prepare prepare therefore to meet the Lord, by true and unfained repentance; for of a truth, the Lord God of Heaven and Earth is ariſen, and riſing in dread to touch the whole earth;<note place="margin">2 Pet: 3.4, 5, 6, 7.</note> ſay not therefore in your hearts, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his coming? for ſince the fathers fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation,</hi> as a people willing to yeeld unto ignorance, and voyd of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>How that by the Word of God, the Heavens were of old, and the Earth, ſtanding out of the water, and in the water, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the world that then was, being overflowed with water periſhed;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60053:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But the Heavens and the Earth which are now by the ſame Word are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto fire againſt the day of Judgement, and perdition of ungodly men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To your own therefore returne, departing from your fore-fathers traditions, examine your ſelves, try your ſelves, prove your hearts, and ſee what you have, which will be able to ſtand in the day of tryall, and not conſume in the burning fire of the Lord God, whereby <hi>the Heavens ſhall be ſet as in flames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet: 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>and the Earth and Elements ſhall melt with the fervent heare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> and all the workes that are in the earth ſhall be burnt up; and ſeeing then that all theſe things ſhall be quickly diſſolved, <hi>what manner of perſons ought ye to be, in all holy converſation and godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Feare, feare, dread, and tremble, tremble before the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, all ye hard and cruell, high and lofty, bow down ye Cedars of the hills, and come down ye ſtrong Oakes of the mountaines, unto the lowlineſſe of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, the Lord God will ſtop the wayes of the Savages of the Foreſts, and place Strength in the path of the Lyons of the Wilderneſſe, and their fierceneſſe ſhall no longer devoure the prey; the ſtrong ſhall ſtarve with hunger, woe to the Deſerts, the Lyon for her whelps, and the Beare for her young as being robbed, as being ſpoyled and deſtroyed, they ſhall roare toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſhall run and not have remedy, they ſhall ſeek and not have reſt, for behold the word of the Lord ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in the Earth upon the Herds, and concerning the flocks upon the Shepherds, and upon the Paſtors, and the end ſhall be the conſumption of all fleſh, which hath corrupted its way upon the face of the earth before the Lord; and with this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the determination of time, which ſhall never bring end to the torment of the wicked, and whoſoever worketh and loveth a lye.</p>
            <p>O Earth, Earth, heare therefore thy warning, and all the Inhabitants thereof, give eare to the ſound of the voyce in the day of your viſitation; the commandement ſtandeth not far from you, neither is the Word ſeparate in another Nation, ſo as that you ſhould ſay, Our arme reacheth not over the Sea to bring it from thence, and who can touch Heaven to bring it down from thence, but the Word is very nigh unto you,<note place="margin">Deut: 30.14,</note> 
               <hi>in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60053:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
your mouth, and in your heart,</hi> that ye may alſo heare it, and do it;<note place="margin">2 Pet: 1.19.</note> Therefore unto the <hi>more ſure word of Propheſie, whereunto ye do well if ye take heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, untill the day dawne, and the day-ſtarre ariſe in your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Light which through Judgement and condemnation, in the ſecret parts of your minds and hearts, preacheth and propheſieth wrath, woe, and the juſt indignation of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all unrighteouſneſſe; this ſure word is nigh you, and with you in your beds, in the fields and ſtreets, and market places, the Light which convinceth you of lying and ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and double-dealing, and all manner of wickedneſſe, if you love it and liſſen unto the checks of it in your hearts and minds, and ſo come to follow the Light, which convinceth you in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of lying and ſwearing, and vaine jeſting, and fooliſh and wanton geſtures and communication; the Light in all your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, wherewith you are lightened, which convinceth you of your ſins, will lead you out of your ſins, and ſo will come to witneſſe ſanctified hearts unto God, and you will come to feele your hearts given up unto ſanctification, and your minds unto the things of Gods kingdome; and by the Light alſo, you will come to diſcerne the two ſeeds, and the two natures, and you will grow unto the witneſſe of the Judgement of the one, from the promiſe of <hi>Sion,</hi> unto the habitation of the heritage of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> whoſe mountaines are places for <hi>Dragons;</hi> And the other unto the Juſtification of life to be made partaker of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of life, and filled with the vertue of the Lord, in wiſdome and a good underſtanding, which the world cannot receive, unto the true knowledge of the Scriptures, unto the witneſſe of them fulfilled in you, which through faith in Chriſt Jeſus, the true <hi>Light,</hi> which lighteth every man that cometh into the world,<note place="margin">Eph: 5.13.</note> are able <hi>to make one wiſe unto ſalvation;</hi> for as all things and deeds which are done and wrought out of the Light, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Light, even ſo alſo <hi>that which maketh manifeſt is light,</hi> and the Light wherewith you are lightened, is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the gift of God, which he hath given unto all men, and the grace of God which hath appeared unto <hi>all men,</hi> which taught the Saints to deny ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, through which (that is to ſay) by the Light, being Judged as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60053:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
men <hi>in the fleſh,</hi> they became Juſtified with God <hi>in the Spirit;</hi> the Light will lead you unto life, if you love it and obey it, according to the voyce of it;<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> therefore <hi>to the Law and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony take heed, ſpeaking alwayes according to this word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye <hi>Greekes</hi> in all quarters and parts of the earth, read this commandement, as the quick ſharp and ſhort meſſage of the Lord unto you, even of the Righteous God, whom your fathers provoked unto wrath, through their Idolatrous ſuperſtitions and all manner of abomination, for which cauſe he brought their necks under the miſerable yoak of bondage, to draw under the cords and chaine of the ſame Inſtrument of cruelty of the <hi>Jewes</hi> captivitie; and this came to paſſe, if peradventure in the time of trouble, they might early ſeek, and cry unto the Lord with unfained hearts, but from generation to generation, even to the evill dayes of this preſent generation, he hath not found Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in your Land, and therefore could not your Land finde nor feel the day of deliverance, and breach of the bowes of your yoaks, by his hand of Redemption; Repent therefore, leſt ye be made an utter ſpoyle, even unto the determination of time, and there come no end of your miſery and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Remember the declaration of the dayes of old, and the ſayings concerning the times which are already paſt; there were a people unto whom the ſure teſtimonies of God were given, but they forſooke the mercy, and through hard-heartedneſſe, and ſelf-conceitedneſſe departed from the fountaine, to aske councell of their own wills, in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 49.6.</note> they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the Covenant in their way; wherefore when Chriſt the Light came contrary to their conceptions, they rather reſiſted unto death, then choſe to be gathered unto life; they once had the Law and the Prophets, and the teſtimony of the Law, and the Arke of the Covenant, and the Temple which God gave them, and yet becauſe of their unbeliefe, God ſpared not the <hi>Jewes,</hi> which were the naturall branches, according to the promiſe; Heare this all ye Gentiles throughout the earth,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>If God ſpared not the naturall branches, becauſe of their unbeliefe,</hi> why boaſt ye your ſelves againſt the naturall branches, who are your ſelves fallen from the Root? If God ſpared not the <hi>Jewes</hi> who received not the Light, which teſtified for Chriſt, which was, and is the Light, which ſhined in all their Conſciences?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60053:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Shall he ſpare you who deſpiſe the Light, and in Enmitie to Chriſt, who is the Light, walke contrary to the Light in all your Conſciences? Behold the goodneſſe and the ſeveritie of God on them which fell, ſeveritie, but towards the Gentiles which ſtood, goodneſſe, and unto as many as now continue in the good which cometh from God, mercy and peace; but as for ſuch as forſake the Light which comes from Chriſt, even they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fruitfull branches ſhall alſo be cut off, and with God there is no reſpect of perſons; <hi>And if the caſting away of the Jewes were the reconciling of the world, what ſhall the receiving of them be, but your torment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom: 11.13.</note> and the reſurrection of the life of the ſeed from the dead, and the redemption thereof from the bondage of the grave, to the glory of God, Amen?</p>
            <p>Truſt ye not therefore in lying words, even as once the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, ſaying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe;</hi> ſay not in your hearts, the wiſdome of God is the councell of our fathers, ſuch words ſhall not ſave you; or if you farther ſay, that you have <hi>Abraham</hi> to your father, that ſhall not profit you, but rather read your birth of the bond-woman, that you may come to the caſting out of her ſeed and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her wombe; for be it knowne unto you, <hi>God can out of rockes raiſe a remnant, and out of ſtones a ſeed unto Abraham;</hi> for not every one that ſaith <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math: 7.22.</note> ſhall enter, <hi>for many ſhall ſay, we have propheſied in thy Name, and in thy Name have caſt out Devills; and yet it ſhall be ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to them, depart ye curſed workers of iniquitie;</hi> and Virgins alſo looſed the Inheritance, even ſuch as were to ſeek <hi>oyle</hi> when the Lord came;<note place="margin">Math: 25.12.</note> and theſe are States beyond the conditions of all your <hi>Roman</hi> members throughout the earth; &amp; the Scriptures are true in the declaration as Chriſt ſpake, although you are falſe in your words, and wayes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations; and if the doore of the kingdome be ſhut againſt <hi>careleſſe Virgins,</hi> how thinke you that wicked lyers, drunkards, ſwearers, whore-mongers, or harlots ſhall have an entrance therein? therefore, whilſt you have time Repent; This is the ſumme unto the pertaking of the purchaſe, that you follow the Lambe of God, Chriſt the Light of the world, which taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſin of the world, He is the higheſt Prieſt, Prophet, and King, of whom this is the ſigne and teſtimony unto Jew and Gentile, <hi>He hath lightened every man that cometh into the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60053:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
world;</hi> and this is the meſſage unto the whole world, <hi>God is light, and in him is no darkneſſe at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look therefore to your lives, for behold this day is ſet before you, <hi>death and darkneſſe, life and light,</hi> chuſe you whether, if you periſh in your ſins, your blood be upon your own heads; hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth &amp; for ever, prize your time,<note place="margin">Heb: 12.17.</note> Remembering that <hi>Eſau</hi> had a time, but <hi>Eſau</hi> neglected his time, ſo that when he carefully ſought a place of Repentance with teares, he could not finde it.</p>
            <p>This is the teſtimony which we (that do walke in the <hi>light,</hi> as God is in the <hi>light</hi>) do hold; we know that whoſoever is <hi>borne of God,</hi> unto the Inheritance of the kingdome of God, <hi>he ſinneth not,</hi> but he that is begotten of God <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 6, 9.</note>
               <hi>keepeth himſelfe, that wicked one toucheth him not, and we know that we are of God,</hi> and we alſo know, <hi>that the whole world,</hi> who are enemies to God, <hi>lyeth in wickedneſſe;</hi> And we know <hi>that the Sonne of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding, whereby we know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, this is the true God, and Eternall life;</hi> Oh all ye Nations abſtaine from Idolls.</p>
            <p>The Saints by the ſeed of the Apoſtated <hi>Jewes</hi> firſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt were called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and we who have received the ſame teſtimony of Jeſus, by the ſeed of the Apoſtated Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Northern Iſlands, are ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers:</hi> J: P:</p>
            <p>SOme Queries propounded to the <hi>Greekes Patriarke,</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to their Doctors, Prieſts &amp; Paſtors, Univerſities, Schooles and Colledges throughout the compaſſe of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of the rule of their two Catholique Churches in all the earth, by them or any of them to be anſwered, for the ſake of truth, and of ſoules, in how much they are willing to appeare lovers of truth or of ſoules, and are ready to render a reaſon of the hope that is in them according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Word of Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>1</label> WHat is the faith of Jeſus? And what is that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets any into the true faith of Jeſus? Whether is it mens Imaginary conceptions of Jeſus, and the training up of a people in the blinde traditions of men, or only the word of faith, which cometh from Jeſus? yea or nay?</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60053:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>2</label> What is the ſure word of faith, which gives the true and ſound witneſſe of the life of Jeſus only unto worme <hi>Jacob,</hi> and which word is nigh unto all men upon the face of the earth, and yet is that which the ſinner cannot receive unto life, but reſiſts unto death?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>3</label> Can any perſon miniſter the Word, to beget others into the faith of the word of faith, who have not themſelves received the word; and have any received the life of the word, who knowes not the word, yea or nay? And who amongſt you is cleanſed with the word, that is not in the ſtate of ſinne, under deaths bonds of tranſgreſſion, in enmity to the word?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>4</label> Whether can any truly know Chriſt to believe in Chriſt, who never have heard the word of Chriſt? And when and where did any of you ever heare the voyce of the Son of God? And is not that the Phariſees and hypocrites ſtate, to boaſt and ſay that you believe in Chriſt, and have the word of God, and yet never heard immediately the voyce of Chriſt, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>5</label> What is that eare in man which being open cannot heare the voyce of Chriſt, who came to make deafe thoſe that heare, and to give hearing to the deafe? And what is that eare alſo, which ought to heare, and is ſtopt? And that eye which ſeeth and is to be blinded, and that eye which is blinded, which Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to open? Shew plainly the five ſenſes of man, which are ſenſleſſe of the word of God, and ſee if you can anſwer how that man in ſenſe beyond ſenſe, hath the true ſenſe of ſeeing, hearing, feeling, ſavouring, by ſmelling and taſting of the good word of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>6</label> By what was it that the word of life was miniſtred and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto the Spirits in priſon? and what is the Spirit which is the priſoner? and what and where is the priſon? and when did ye ever viſit the priſoner in the time of his bondage in priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the <hi>Patriarke</hi> and <hi>Popes</hi> Power.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>7</label> WHat is the key which openeth the priſon doore? and who hath that key? hath either your <hi>Patriarke</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> that key to open the priſon doore, and to looſe on earth? And what is the matter and ſubject to be looſed on earth? And in what manner will that alſo be looſed in heaven, which is loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on earth?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>8</label> What is the key of <hi>David,</hi> and who hath the keeping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60053:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and is there any other key which openeth Heaven or ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the door of death, or gates of Hell, beſides the key of <hi>David?</hi> Whether either your <hi>Patriarch</hi> or <hi>Pope,</hi> whom ye call <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, hath the keeping of that key? ſeeing that the Scriptures ſay, <hi>That the firſt and the laſt, he that openeth and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth, and no man openeth, hath the key of David,</hi> Rev. 3.7. Rev. 1.17, 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>9</label> What is the key of knowledge which the Lawyers took away, whereby they entered not themſelves, and hindered others from entering, even ſuch as was entering? Did the Lawyers know what that key was then? And do your <hi>Patriarch</hi> or <hi>Pope, Doctors, Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Lawyers,</hi> know what it is now? Are you in any other knowledge or wiſdome then thoſe Lawyers were, who entred not, and hindred others, yea or nay? And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may ſay that you differ, do you ſhew it forth how you differ in the ground and nature? <hi>Luke</hi> 11.52.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>10</label> What is that Book and the Seales, and Sealing of that Book which no man in Heaven nor in Earth was found worthy to open? And where was <hi>Peter</hi> then? whether was he in Heaven or in Earth? or was he neither in Heaven, nor on Earth? and the Scriptures not ſaying, that <hi>Peter</hi> was found worthy at that time, how then can any of your Catholique Churches with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence now ſay, that thoſe whom you call <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors, the Foundations and Pillars of your Churches, are at this time worthy to do that? or whether can your <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Patriarch</hi> do that in theſe dayes, which <hi>John</hi> ſaw in his day <hi>no man in Heaven nor in Earth could do,</hi> Rev. 5.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>11</label> Your Members have ſaid that <hi>Peter</hi> is the Rock and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of your Catholique Churches; I Query whether that was not the <hi>Peter</hi> who is the foundation of your Churches, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom Chriſt (the Rock and Foundation of our Church which is in God) ſaid, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi> and whether is the <hi>Patriarch</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> his ſucceſſor, in his place, yea or nay? <hi>Math.</hi> 16.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>12</label> Doth not the virtue of the key of knowledge open all myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and if ye have the key of knowledge of the things of God, cannot ye thereby anſwer all theſe Queryes or any others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the things of God, in the clear underſtanding of the myſtery of Truth in the wiſdom of God, yea or my?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60053:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>13</label>
                  <hi>Whoſoever committeth ſin is of the Devil,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. What then is the ground of the election of your <hi>Patriarch</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> by ſinners, and impowred to forgive ſins? And in what ſtandeth their power to forgive ſins, who are themſelves wicked ſinners? Whether is the manner of this practice any other in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, then <hi>Satan</hi> ſeating <hi>Lucifer</hi> in the Kingdom of ſin, falſly to ſalve up the wound of ſin, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Ordinances and divers corrupt Traditions and Idolatries.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>14</label> WHat is the one everlaſting Ordinance of God? which is the ſeal of the Covenant, and aſſurance of ſalvation unto every living ſoul, which hath partaked thereof, which no Element could give the teſtimony of, which is the ſum and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (really come unto every true born Member of Chriſts Church) of all Types, Signes and Shadows, which figured out the ſubſtance before it came?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>15</label> Whether are your two Catholique Churches, or any of the Members thereof partakers of the one everlaſting Ordinance of God, which is the end of all waſhing, carnall Bread, Wine, and Water-Baptiſmes, and of all ſhaddows, Types, and Figures, ſpoken of in the Scriptures, ſeeing you in contrary manner to all the propheſies, doctrines, and examples written in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, do ſtand in divers invented ſhaddows, vanities, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, in the practice of the doctrines of your fore-fathers tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, in oppoſition to the power of God, and Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus? Read <hi>Coloſſ:</hi> 1, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>16</label> Where doth the Scripture ſay that to take up Croſſes of Gold, Silver, Braſſe, Iron, Bone, Wood, or carved Stone, made by the invention of man, is to take up the Croſſe of Chriſt, who came not by man, nor according to the will of man, whoſe Croſſe came with him, contrary to the will of man? What is the Image to the ſubſtance? And whether is that any part of the nature of the ſubſtance in you, or doth it not rather ſtand in enmity to the ſubſtance, which taketh up an Image of the Croſſe among you, yea, or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>17</label> Whoſe doctrine or Commandement was the foundation of your Idol Temples? declare plainly, whether God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or Satan deceived? And what rule have you in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or example from the life of the Apoſtles, to worſhip in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60053:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Idols Temples, altogether by the light of wax Candles, or burning Lamps of Oyl, and to keep your wax Candles burning night and day in your Idols Temples?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>18</label> Whether is it not great ignorance for a people to ſeek the Lord out of the habitation and ſanctuary of his holineſſe? Wherefore ſeek ye to find God in Temples made with hands, <hi>Seeing God dwelleth not in Temples made with hands?</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do you not underſtand that thoſe Temples which are not Gods habitation, are the reall Synagogues of Satan, yea or nay? <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>19</label> What rule have you in the Scripture to make a mock of Chriſt, and the holy Apoſtles, by carrying about Images (which ye call their Pictures) by day time, with the light of Candles or Torches through your ſtreets, with many perſons paſſing therewith hood-winked and diſguiſed as Thieves and Robbers, ſinging and rejoycing, and making merry over the ſpoll of the innocent?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>20</label> What rule have you in the Scriptures, or example from the life of the Apoſtles, to light the dead Corps of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the Graves or Sepulchres, with Torches or Wax Candles?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>21</label> What precept have you in the Scriptures to call Elements and ſhaddows, or any of thoſe things, which once were figures, Sacraments, and to carry Bread and Wine through your ſtreets, with a Canopie over it, with Torches or Wax Candles ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and one ringing a Bell before it (like the hypocrires ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Trumpets of their ſervices) and for all people that meets it, to fall down upon their knees before it?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>22</label> What rule have you in the Scriptures, or plain example from the life of the Apoſtles, without adding unto, or diminiſhing from the Scriptures, or the acts of Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, for your ſprinkling Infants with water, and calling that an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt, or Sacrament of your Churches?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>23</label> What precept have you in the Scriptures, or preſident from the life of the Apoſtles, to pray upon Beads, or to pray to Saints, or to <hi>Mary,</hi> and to croſſe your ſelves with your hands in your prayers, or thankſgivings, or to make bowings before walls, croſſing your ſelves with your hands, babling a few words before you go into your Beds?</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60053:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>24</label> What precept or example have you in the Scriptures, to make Inquiſitions and Inquiſitors, to ſlay the life of Gods wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt your Idolatries, and to make Fryaryes and Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neryes, Doctors, Fryars, Nuns, Jeſuits, lay-brothers, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, Queriſters, Singers, &amp; Ringers, were ever ſuch prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, ſhould come in the Truth, or were ever ſuch in their dayes, yea or nay:</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>25</label> Where did Chriſt ever teach, or the Apoſtles practice the wearing of the garments, and long robes of the ſeveral Officers of your Catholique Churches, your long Gowns and Surplices, and whipping Cords about your Loyns, and other Girdles, and Caps, and other disfiguring garments?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>26</label> What rule have you in the Scriptures, or example from the life of the Apoſtles, for your grey Fryars, crown-head ſhavings, and for your other Officers with their great Bottles, Wallets, and begging Bags, and others with many Boxes, in diſguiſed and hood-winked garments, going through the ſtreets, and from houſe to houſe a begging?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>27</label> What rule have you in the Scriptures, or example from the life of the Apoſtles, for your obſerving ſet times and dayes of the week and year, to eat Fiſh or Herbs, or other fruit, and no Fleſh, as in your Lents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to call ſuch dayes Faſt-dayes, ſeeing you eat no fleſh, but do eat and drink your fill of other creatures, and ſome with ſtrong drink or Wine, do make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves drunk upon ſuch dayes?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>28</label> What precept or preſident have you from the doctrine or life of Chriſt or his Apoſtles, for ſome of your members to whip and ſcourge themſelves upon ſome ſet dayes of the year, and to draw blood from their bodyes, and to make bruiſes and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in their fleſh, and for others of your Officers to lay hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burdens upon the backs of ſome your Members, which they themſelves will not touch with one of their fingers; to make poor people go upon their knees through the ſtreets, as far as they pleaſe, for the obtaining from them the Remiſſion of their ſins; and are not you abominably deceitful as well in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as in the matter of this iniquity, in laying only ſuch ſhame and puniſhment upon the poor in the world, and do not lay the ſame upon a tranſgreſſor in the ſame luſt and nature, who is very powerfull in the Authority, and rich and wealthy in the world?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60053:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>29</label> What precept or preſident have you from the doctrine or life of Chriſt or his Apoſtles to keep and obſerve dayes and times and ſeaſons, which ye call Saints dayes, ſaying that ye keep them in honour of the perſons of Chriſt and his Apoſtles? Are ye not rather a diſhonour and ſtain of their life, who ſpend ſuch dayes in Idolatries, in ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs, <hi>in chambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and wantonneſſe,</hi> Coloſſ. 2.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>30</label> Whether is there any one among you that do witneſſe Chriſt come in you? which he that witneſſeth not Chriſt ſo come in the fleſh is Antichriſt; and if Chriſt be come in the fleſh, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in you, why then do ye with your fleſh make Images of the fleſh, for your corruptible fleſh to bowe unto? and whileſt the ſpirit which rules your fleſh, doth thus dictate and lead you, doth not your minds in the fleſh make a mock of Chriſt, who is a Spirit, and of God, who will only be worſhipped in ſpirit, yea or nay? 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. In theſe Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, deceitful ſhaddows, and Idolatries, profeſſing the name of Chriſt, enemies to the power of the Croſſe, and order of the doctrine and myſtery of the life of Chriſt, ye are a juſt occaſion of ſtumbling to the <hi>Turk,</hi> and an offence to the ſeed in the <hi>Jew;</hi> and this the Lord God will require at the hands of your two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Myſtery of the Holy Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>31</label> What is the ſeed of the Kingdome of Heaven, which is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, and how comes it to grow to a Tree, and how come the birds of the Aire to lodge therein, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it fruitfull before it be grafted, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>32</label> What and where is the field, in which the Pearl is hid? and what is the Pearl to the field, how are they diſtinguiſhed? and how is the Pearl hid? and by what comes the purchaſe of the field? and how comes the Pearl to be found? and who are they that have found it, and do keep it having found it, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>33</label> What is the ſeed of God, unto which only the promiſe of God, of ſalvation, unto life everlaſting, is?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>34</label> What was the Image of God which man loſt through the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and tranſgreſſion againſt the will and commandement of God, and whether all that ſtand in the diſobedient and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtate, are not ſtill ſeated in the loſt ſtate, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>35</label> How lyes the Image of God now in the duſt, and what is the duſt to the Image of God? and what is the Serpent? and how
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60053:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doth the Serpent feed upon the duſt of the ground? and what is that ground which is not at all ſubſtantial, but duſty, and that ground whoſe ſubſtance is mountains, ſtony and rocky, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther barren and unfruitful?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>36</label> By what comes the change of the ground? <hi>Moab</hi> alſo hath been at eaſe from his youth, &amp; hath not bin emptied from veſſel to veſſel; what is <hi>Moabs</hi> ſeed now, which in the nature ſtands in the ſame ſtate that <hi>Moab</hi> was then? &amp; whether are ye in any other condition or life then as ye were from the beginning? &amp; as ye have grown in years, ſo you have grown in wickedneſs; whether therefore do ye beleeve that it is poſſible for you to be ſaved, except the ground be changed, &amp; <hi>Moab</hi> emptied, &amp; ye become begotten &amp; born of God unto another life? &amp; whether doth he that is born of God commit ſin, yea or nay? <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.11. <hi>John</hi> 3.3. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>37</label> What is the ſalvation of Jeſus? from what doth he firſt ſave his people? In plain words ſhew to all people, what is Salvation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and Reſtauration, and from what, unto what, and when?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>38</label> What is that life of Chriſt, which is ſlain in ſpiritual <hi>Sodom,</hi> which is daily crucified upon the Croſſes of your Catholique Churches?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>39</label> What manner of fruit bare that <hi>Almond Tree,</hi> of which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaw a rod? &amp; what is that <hi>ſeething pot,</hi> which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> alſo did ſee? and what is the fleſh which for one day muſt boyle therein? and whether a root and fruit ought to be boyled with the fleſh? and whether will the Broth of theſe things be clean food according to the Law, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>40</label> What is that new threſhing inſtrument which is prepared for the hand of worm <hi>Jacob</hi> to threſh withall? how ſhall he threſh the hills to Chaffe, and mountains to duſt? and with what ſhall be fan them? and what is the wind that ſhall carry them away? and where ſhall the chaffe be carried? and in what quarters ſhall the whirle-wind ſcatter the duſt of the mountains?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>41</label> Whether the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the Kingdom, which Chriſt ſaid is like to a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, and the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and worm <hi>Jacob,</hi> are they in the ſubſtance one, two, three or four, yea or nay? &amp; ſhew plainly without deceit, how that two three or all are one in the ſubſtance, or otherwiſe make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt how in the declaration, ſo alſo they differ in the ſubſtance?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>42</label> What is the new creation of God? whether is it now ſhort of the creation of the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> whom God made a living ſoul? do any of you believe that the ſecond is made a quickning ſpirit?
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60053:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and which of theſe two is the greater, and moſt full of glory? are any of ye paſſed from death unto life, from the diſhonour of ſin &amp; tranſgreſſion, to ſee the beauty of the firſt Creation, and to behold the honour of the Lord from Heaven? doe ye beleeve the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Son of God, yea or nay? Shew how Chriſt hath revealed himſelf unto any one of you, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>43</label> What and where ſtandeth the Tree of Life, which he that comes to eat thereof, ſhall never taſte of death, and which he that taſteth not thereof in this life, ſhall never ſee the day of life? have any one or more of you, in all your Nations, and two Catholique Churches ever ſeen a leaf of the Tree of Life, which healeth the Nations, and deſcribe how, and by what wind any leaf was blown upon any of your Nations, and ſhew forth thoſe that are healed thereby of your Nations?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>44</label> Whether do you believe the real, ſubſtantial, everlaſting virtue of the blood of Jeſus? If you anſwer yea, why then in abominable deceit, and miſerable ignorance, do you teach for doctrine an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal place of purgatory? Read the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. and what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageth the peoples pennance, and the <hi>Popes</hi> and Prieſts remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, if after pennance, repentance, and remiſſion, they muſt go into the torment of Purgatory to be cleanſed from their ſins, to enter into the Kingdome of Heaven?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>45</label> What and where is the Sanctuary of God ſeated, wherein the Saints of God do daily worſhip, and what is the equall ballance thereof, and the duſt of the ballance? Declare plainly what is that which meaſureth juſtly all words, works, worſhips, ſtudyes, wayes and ſpirits, which reacheth over iniquity, and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the myſtery thereof, what is that line which meaſureth the worlds wayes, and the plummet unto which judgement is laid? and what is that Reed which <hi>John</hi> had to meaſure the Temple of God, &amp; the Altar thereof? and what is that Court which he was not to meaſure, which the Gentiles tread under foot?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the ſtudies in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, of Tongues, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Aſtrologie, Phyſick, Law and Philoſophy.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>46</label> WHat is the foundation &amp; chief corner ſtone of your Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities &amp; Colledges; &amp; do you not reckon <hi>Tongues, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, Philoſophy,</hi> to be precedent ſteps leading unto <hi>Theologie,</hi> to the compleating of a Miniſtry, &amp; as the principle leaders unto the expert practice of <hi>Phyſick, Law, Aſtrologie?</hi> and whether are not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60053:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
theſe Arts and Sciences, the ſum, ſubſtance, and end of your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>47</label> Whether only the word of God is not the real ſubſtance of the miniſtry of God? &amp; the ground of underſtanding &amp; true knowledg of all the natural; &amp; whether all Tongues, Arts and Sciences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the word are not vanity? and whether all that profeſſe the ſubſtance yet ſtanding in the naturall, and have not the word from God, as from the mouth of God, are not in vanity and deceit, and in utter enmity to the word, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>48</label> Who is he of all your <hi>Patriarchs, Popes, Doctors, Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> let him ſtand forth and anſwer by name, which hath received the word as from the mouth of God, to miniſter it faithfully, as the everlaſting Goſpel and meſſage of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>49</label> Who is the <hi>Aſtronomer</hi> or <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> let him ſtand forth and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by name, which hath received the word, &amp; dwels in the word, by which the earth &amp; the Sea, &amp; all that in them are, &amp; the heavens the Sun, Moon, &amp; Stars, the habitations of the heavens, &amp; the hoſts of the Heavens were made, which made all, &amp; governs all, even unto this day, to building &amp; deſtroying, to planting &amp; plucking up, which ſhews the natural cauſes of all overtures &amp; changes? And let him anſwer me with the ſtrength of his underſtanding, whether his predictions are not ſubject to alter &amp; change, or are they altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unalterable &amp; infallible? And this will manifeſt the original to be either the word of the Lord, or the ſpirit of the Devil; let him tell me whether worm <hi>Jacob</hi> hath a habitation in his houſe, or ſhew me how the ſeed of worm <hi>Jacob</hi> is governed in his houſe, which if he knows not that, how knows he in what manner the Plannets are governed, and Signes are ordered in and about the houſe of Heaven, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.25. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.7, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>50</label> What is the ground &amp; cauſe of every diſeaſe which is generated in the nature of mankind; &amp; whether you <hi>Docters</hi> do know the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Symptoms of the nature of the diſeaſes? and have you the figure of that root in your Herbal, which is the ſubſtantial &amp; effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual cure of ſuch diſeaſes, &amp; how &amp; in what manner ought than root to be applyed as a Remedy for the cure of the malady, and ſaving of the ſick, which if ye knew the virtue, and were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto all perſons, conſidering their conditions, in adminiſtring an equal portion of that root, would not your practices preach a teſtimony to the diſcovering of the iniquities of all, that makes a prey upon the people for the love of their monies, yea or nay?</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60053:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>51</label> What is the ground of a juſt Law? Let the Judges, Juſtices, and Lawyers anſwer, whether they ſtand in that ground which was the originall of the Law given unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> or are any of them in that ground wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> received the Law? Whether are they graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the roote of righteouſneſſe, wherein the good Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Lawes is teſtified to be the preſervation of peace in the Nations, which if they anſwer affirmatively: I further Query; What is the little meaſure of equitie which meaſureth all cauſes, and dealeth juſt Judgement unto all without reſpect of perſons, in all manner of differences, ſuits and controverſies between man and man, as in one Law and way of equitie and truth, which if the Judges &amp; Juſtices did Judge by that Law, and the Lawyers plead from the ground of that Law, the Innocent would no longer ſuffer, nor the oppreſſed groane under cruelties, through the execution of corruption under the name of a Juſt Law?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>52</label> What is the tongue of the learned; diſtinguiſh that which is but one from the tongues of mens learning, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are many in the world? and whether any tongues beſide that one, in any meaſure reacheth to the underſtanding of the things of God, yea or nay? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>53</label> Whether is Philoſophy in contrariety unto, or in unitie with the tongue of the learned? and what is the originall roote of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, and ground of Philoſophy? and can any receive the tongue of the Learned, to ſpeak forth the things of God, in the wiſdome of God, in whom the ground of Philoſophy, and roote of Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick remaines? and is not the roote knowne by the branch, leafe, and bloſſome, which ſprings from the roote, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>54</label> What Bottle is that which is only proper to receive in it the old wine of Rhetorick, and dregges of Philoſophy? And what Bottle is that which receiveth only the new wine of the kingdom? and whether is it poſſible, that theſe two can be contained in one bottle, without breaking the bottle? And what is the old bottle which cannot hold new wine? Whether are not you that old bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which never was broken, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>55</label> What ayre is that wherein <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid the Saints ſhall meet the Lord? whether is it one of the foure Elements of which the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers ſaid mans naturall body is compoſed of? Whether is it a naturall Element that ſhall for ever comprehend Chriſt, and the Saints ſpirituall life? ſeeing <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, and ſo ſhall we be ever with the Lord. But if ye ſay that that ayre is not one of the Elements which the Philoſophers wrote of, anſwer then according
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60053:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the Scripture, and ſhew by the witneſſe of God, what that ayre is, if not an Element? 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>56</label> Whether doth not your Philoſophy informe you, that if there be a third, of neceſſitie alſo there muſt be a ſecond and a firſt, which ye Doctors of <hi>Athens,</hi> or other Officers of the two Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Churches throughout the earth need not have gon to <hi>Rome,</hi> or other Colledges or Schooles to have learned, ſeeing moſt of the meane and vulgar in your accounts could ſo farre informe you, in your own places and ſtreets; But without controverſie, to the ends of the earth you muſt firſt goe, ere you come in truth to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this my Query: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid that he knew a man which was caught up into the third heaven; what was the firſt heaven, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Paul</hi> made his firſt entrance, coming out of the Jawes and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of death? And what was the ſecond heaven, and the third heaven, in which he ſaw the Revelation of things unlawfull to be uttered? And whether the firſt, ſecond, or third heaven is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, but equall, or above the ayre which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of? And finally ſpeak plainly, whether can a man in his will, by his wit or wiſdome politicall, his knowledge hiſtoricall, the exerciſe of his arts and parts ſylogiſticall or philoſophicall, or by any of your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes Theologicall throughout your Univerſities and Colledges, Anſwer theſe Queries concerning the things of God, according to truth in the wiſdome of God, to ſpeak as the Oracles of God, yea or nay? 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <p>All ye Officers of the two Catholique Churches, if truth be with you, you will be glad of an occaſion to Anſwer, and lay open the deceits and Errors of hereticks, for the confirmation of every honeſt heart, and eſtabliſhing all ſimple ſouls in the doctrine of truth. Be wiſe in your generation, for your owne actions will te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie in the hearts of the people, either for you, or againſt you. Fury may proclaime a fire in your boſomes, and you may order this writing to be burnt with fire, but that will publiſh your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and preach your ſpirits to be of the author of murder; I tell you in time, ſuch an action will work your own confuſion, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards God of a truth will plead with you by fire: Truth is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove deceit, and can ſtop the mouth of the deceiver, and gaine-ſayer; but the worker of iniquitie ſeeketh to hide his head with a cover. For the truth ſake ſimply this is given forth, by one who hath counted all things loſſe, that he might gaine the truth.</p>
               <p>Your anſwers will ſavour of the beſt Zeale, which ye may ſend
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60053:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
directed, to be delivered unto <hi>Gerrard Roberts,</hi> dwelling at the ſigne of the <hi>Flowerdeluce</hi> in <hi>Thomas Apoſtles</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for him whom men call <hi>John Perrott.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THough they ſay the Lord liveth, ſurely they ſweare falſly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jere: 5.2.</note> ſaith <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> All Doctors, Prieſts, and Paſtors, that do preach and declare with their tongues Chriſt to be <hi>the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> and yet walk contrary to the light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, ſuch are lyers and falſe ſwearers, for Chriſt unto them is not <hi>the way,</hi> neither in them is he <hi>the truth, or the life,</hi> who walk contrary to the light, wherewith they are lightened; <note place="margin">Joh: 8.12. Joh: 1.4.</note>
                  <hi>I am the light of the world,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> ſaith <hi>John,</hi> who was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the way, and of the truth, and of the life, who himſelfe not his words, was neither the way, the truth, nor the life; for his teſtimony was true concerning Chriſt, who is the way, the truth,<note place="margin">Joh: 14.6.</note> and the life. <hi>Paul, Peter, Mark, Luke, Mathew, John</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> they alſo were witneſſes of the true light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, whoſe teſtimony was of Jeſus the Chriſt, they were not that Chriſt, neither were their words, or writings, or Epiſtles that Chriſt, which they by their words and writings before all men bare witneſſe of, who is the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, which is the way, the truth, and the life, which is the word of God,<note place="margin">Joh: 1.1. Iſa: 42.6.</note> of whom and by whom, <hi>the worlds were made;</hi> and the Prophets propheſied of things to come to paſſe, which are come to paſſe, and coming to paſſe, which teſtified of the light, <hi>which is come into the world, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every one that cometh into the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa: 49.6.</note> according to the word of propheſie.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures do not ſay that they are the word, but they ſay that by the word which was in the beginning, which was with God, and was God, the heavens and the earth was made, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scriptures was, by which word, the Scriptures came to be written, which ſaith that the name of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rev: 19.13.</note> who is the light of the world, is called the <hi>word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now all that ſay that the words of the Prophets and Apoſtles is the way to life, they are out of the way, ſpeaking in the darkneſſe of this world, their teſtimony is falſe, and they are Antichriſt, for the way is but one, and Chriſt is that way to the father, who is the light of the world, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, for the Scriptures and writings of the Apoſtles they were
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60053:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not before the world was, neither do they ſay they were written <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was, but the way, and the word, was unto <hi>Abel,</hi> and <hi>Seth,</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.6.</note> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> which was before the Scriptures was; and the Scriptures teſtifies theſe things, ſaying Chriſt is the way, in wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt thoſe which ſay <hi>the Scriptures is the way;</hi> and the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt is the word, in witneſs againſt thoſe that ſay <hi>the Scriptures is the word;</hi> and the Scriptures ſay that Chriſt is the life, in witneſs againſt thoſe that ſay <hi>the Scriptures is the Rule of life and truth;</hi> and the Scriptures ſay, Chriſt is the light, in witneſs againſt thoſe that ſay the Scriptures is the <hi>light;</hi> and the Scriptures ſay,<note place="margin">Joh. 12.46.</note> that Chriſt is the truth, in teſtimony and witneſs againſt all thoſe that ſay <hi>the Scriptures of truth</hi> (which witneſſes againſt all their deceits &amp; lyes, which is the ſure declaration of truth) <hi>is the truth.</hi> Theſe things are written in the Scriptures, which declare the way to be one, the truth one, the life one, the word one, all one, Chriſt who is the one true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; A meaſure of which teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in every mans conſcience, againſt lying, and ſwearing, &amp; flattering, and cheating, &amp; double-dealing, &amp; adultery, and drunkenneſs, &amp; pride, &amp; cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, &amp; ſtealing, &amp; oppreſſion, and envie, and murder, and all ſin; the light hath ſhined in every mans conſcience, and this is the Law of God which was nigh unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> which is among the Heathen which have not the Scriptures, the Scriptures is not written in their conſciences, but the light hath ſhined in all their conſciences, &amp; the ſame which judgeth the hearts which hath not the Scriptures, alſo judgeth thoſe who profeſſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; yet in their lives walk contrary to the Scriptures. The light which lighteneth Jew and Gentile, is the condemnation both of Jew and Gentile, of as many as walk contrary to the light, wherewith they are lighteneth and this is the condemnation,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>light is come into the world, but men love dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 1.4.</note>But now the light is life to all that love it &amp; follow it, &amp; ſuch as obey the light, the light maketh alive; the Scripture is not the Spirit which quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; you that can but reade the letter, do you read the letter, and the letter will tell you, <hi>That the letter killeth, but the ſpirit maketh alive;</hi> if you believe that the letter is the life, then that which you believe is the life, tels you that <hi>the letter kills,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.6.</note> which is, deſtruction of the life, &amp; what profit have you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the letter? Therefore to the light keep your minds, waiting in it, that you may be governed by the Light which cometh from Chriſt, by it to be led unto Chriſt, that you may come to know him to be the Captain &amp; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Iſrael</hi> unto ſalvation;<note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> let the light rule your hearts, and the affections of your hearts and minds, that you may have feeling of the rule of God, the light is the meaſure &amp; rule of truth in all your hearts, which will lead you into all truth unto life,<note place="margin">Joh. 16.13.</note> if you love it and follow it, but will ſtand your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation even unto the end unto death, if you hate it, and walk contrary to it. Look to <hi>Abels</hi> rock, to <hi>Enoch</hi> his path, to <hi>Moſes</hi> his way, to <hi>David</hi> throne of Judgement, to the Prophets hope, to the Saints ſalvation, waite to receive this as the foundation of your age,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11, 12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>for other foundation can no more lay, then that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt, the true light of the world, which ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth every man that cometh into the world;</hi> and the day ſhall declare every mans work, whether it be gold, ſilver, or pretious ſtone, wood, hay, droſſe, chaffe, or ſtubble, it ſhall all be revealed by the fire of the Lord God, which is already kindled in the earth. Therefore whilſt you have time, Repent</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
